<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="LEDA_ODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
   rendition="lilielbe.org/context/Letters/1933-01-09HoyerSchrembs.html"
   xml:base="https://gitlab.com/ctsdh/lili-elbe-code/raw/master/XSLT_sandbox/readingViews/input/letters/19330109HoyerSchrembs.xml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>
               <date when="1933-01-09">1933-01-09</date> Letter to <persName key="schrembsCarl">Carl
                  Schrembs</persName>
            </title>
            <author>
               <persName key="hoyerNiels" role="AUT">Niels Hoyer</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Translation completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="twj" role="TRL">Tatjana Willms-Jones</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Translation reviewed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sm">Sabine Meyer</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by </resp>
               <persName ref="twj">Tatjana Willms-Jones</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="co">Colin O'Connell</persName>
               <persName ref="swv">Susan VanDerveer</persName>
               <persName ref="bt">Brenda Torres</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance and/or XML proofing completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="ccm">Caroline McCraw</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML transformed into HTML
                     <date><!-- exact transformation date generated during transformation; leave this one alone --></date>
                  by</resp>
               <persName ref="rjp">Rebecca J. Parker</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>HTML proofing completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="ccm">Caroline McCraw</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Images prepared by</resp>
               <persName ref="mg">Matthew Gallagher</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Loyola University Chicago Libraries</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Loyola's Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Lili Elbe Digital Archive</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="2019-07-06">July 6th, 2019</date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName select="source" key="EHA">Ernst Harthern Archives,
                     Arbetarrörelsens Arkiv och Bibliotek (Swedish Labour Movement's Archives and
                     Library)</orgName> in <placeName>Huddinge, Sweden</placeName>.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc source="Manuscript" xml:lang="ger">
            <p>A one-page, two-sided typed letter with no distingushing features (no holes, no
               emendations)</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy source="https://arc-staging.dh.tamu.edu/index.php/Submitting_RDF">
               <category source="collex" xml:id="discipline">
                  <catDesc>History/Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category source="collex" xml:id="genre">
                  <catDesc>Correspondence</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category source="collex" xml:id="text">
                  <catDesc>https://gitlab.com/ctsdh/lili-elbe-code/raw/master/XSLT_sandbox/plainText/output/1933-01-09HoyerSchrembs.txt</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category source="dc" xml:id="date">
                  <catDesc>1933</catDesc></category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <hyphenation>
               <p>We have removed the hyphenation that appears in the printed text during
                  digitization and encoding. Original hyphenation can be consulted in the facsimile
                  images.</p>
            </hyphenation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="original">
            <pb style="page" facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/letters/1933-01-09HoyerSchrembs01.jpg"/>
            <div rend="head" style="letter">
               <p><date>9.1.33.</date></p>
               <p>Herrn</p>
               <p><persName key="schrembsCarl">Driektor Carl Th.Schrembs</persName></p>
               <p>München 0 51</p>
               <p>Haralaching 3</p>
            </div>
            <div rend="body">
               <p>Sehr geehrter <persName key="schrembsCarl">Herr Schrembs</persName>!</p>
               <p>Ich denke Ihnen sehr herzlich fuer Ihre freundl- ichen Worte über mein <persName
                     key="lili">Lili Elbe</persName> Buch.</p>
               <p>Ihr Brief ist nicht der erste, der deswegen Fragen an mich richtet und Aufschlüsse
                  fordert. Daraus sehe ich, wie rich- tig es war, dass ich das Buch ediert habe.</p>
               <p>Sie fragen u.a., ob es stimmt, dass <persName key="lili">Lili</persName> an
                  Herzschwäche ge- storben sei. Nun, <persName key="warnekros">Professor
                     Warnekros</persName> braucht nichts zu ver- heimlichen: <persName key="lili"
                     >Lilis</persName> Tod steht in keinem ursächlichen Zusam- menhang mit den an
                  ihrem Körper durch <persName key="warnekros">W.</persName> usgeführten not-
                  wendigen Operationen. Ein altes Nierenleiden, an dem bereits vor vielen Jahren
                     <persName key="wegenerE">Einar (Andreas)</persName> vorübergehend gelitten, kam
                  plötzlich wieder zum Ausbruch. Das war ein paar Wochen nach der letzten, völlig
                  gelungenen Operation.- Ein Nierenleiden wirkt sich auf das Herz aus, überanstrengt
                  das Herz…</p>
               <p>Zu einem Zwe ifel an den Angaben <persName key="warnekros"
                     >Professor Warnekros</persName> liegt also nicht der mindeste Anlass vor.
                  Uebrigens war er gar nicht in <placeName key="dresden">Dresden</placeName>,
                  sondern in <placeName key="franceSouth">Suedfrankreich</placeName>, als n a c h
                  der wohlgelungenen letzten Operation der plötzlichen, anschein- bare Rückschlag
                  eintrat: das alte Nierenleiden.- Im Augen- blick weiss ich nicht genau, ob
                     <persName key="lili">Lili</persName> oder <persName key="sparreAn"
                     >Andreas</persName> ueberhaupt jemals <persName key="warnekros">Prof.
                     W.</persName> gegenüber eine Andeutung von dem alten Nie- renleiden gemacht
                  hat; ich glaube es nicht einmal. Mir gegen- über, dem <persName key="lili"
                     >Lili</persName> alles, aber auch a l l e s beichtete, hat sie nie erzählt,
                  dass <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> jemals nierenleidend war.</p>
               <p>Krebs hat <persName key="lili">Lili</persName> nicht gehabt. Das ist Legende. Dass
                  Neider <persName key="warnekros">Prof.W.</persName> etwas am Zeuge herumflicken
                  möchten, ist, wie wir Menschen nun einmal sind, verständlich. Dass ohne <persName
                     key="warnekros">Prof. W.s</persName> eingreifen <persName key="wegenerE"
                     >Einar</persName> bereits viele Monate vorher gestorben wäre, steht
                  zweifelsfrei fest. Man lese <persName key="lili">Lilis</persName> letzte Briefe an
                  mich. Uebrigens hat <persName key="warnekros">Prof. W.</persName> mein Manuskript
                  bis zum Ausklang vor Drucklegung gelesen und daran sage und schreibe noch nicht
                  einmal 30 Zeilen korrigiert.- </p>
               <p>Ich bin sehr gern bereit, mit Ihnen in Briefwechsel zu blei- ben. Jeder Ihrer
                  Briefe wird eine verständnisvolle Antwort finden. In 2 bis 3 Jahren will ich auf
                  Grundlage meines <persName key="lili">Lili Elbe</persName> Buches einen Roman
                  schreiben, der diesen problematischen “Seelen- und Körper-Fall“ (wenn man sich so
                  ausdrücken darf) von der rein dichterischen Warte aus betrachten wird. Ich be-
                  sitze noch anderes, noch nicht veröffentlichtes Material von <pb style="page" n="2"
                     facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/letters/1933-01-09HoyerSchrembs02.jpg"/><persName key="lili"
                     >Lili</persName>, das ich erst später, dichterisch behandelt, verarbeiten will
                  und kann.</p>
               <p>Sie waren so lieb, mich nach <placeName key="munich">München</placeName> einzuladen. Ich
                  komme sicherlich in absehbarer Zeit einmal nach dort. Ich werde Ihnen dann
                  rechtzeitig Nachricht geben.</p>
               <p>Sie sprechen auch von <persName key="garlandM">meiner Frau</persName>, die Sie
                  durch mein Buch auch schon kennen gelernt hätten…? Das dürfte ein Irrtum sein. Von
                  ihr habe ich nie gesprochen. Wohl hat sie mit <persName key="lili">Lili</persName>
                  viel korrespondiert, auch hier oft mit ihr gesprochen. Aber im Buch ist davon nie
                  die Rede. Vielleicht verwechseln Sie sie mit meiner Tochter <persName key="ruth">R
                     u t h</persName>, der einzigen Schülerin von <persName key="lili"
                     >Lili</persName>?</p>
               <p>Selbstredend betrachte ich die Korrespondenz mit Ihnen als vertraulich.</p>
               <p>Was übrigens bedeutet: Direktor der M.T.A.G.?</p>
               <p>Mit den besten Grüssen</p>
               <signed>Ihr ergebener</signed>
               <postscript>
                  <p>Esdürfte Sie vielleicht interessieren, dass mein Buch in <placeName
                        key="london">London</placeName>, <placeName key="newYork">New
                        Jork</placeName>, <placeName key="budapest">Budapest</placeName>, <placeName
                        key="paris">Paris</placeName>, <placeName key="belgrad">Belgrad</placeName>
                     etc. in einigen Monaten er- scheinen wird. Falls Sie in den Zeitungen
                        <placeName>Münchens</placeName> Besprechun- gen find n sollten, wäre ich
                     Ihnen dankbar, wenn Sie mir Aus- schnitte zusenden könnten.-</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="translation">
            <div rend="head" style="letter">
               <p><date>1/9/33</date></p>
               <p>Mr.</p>
               <p><persName key="schrembsCarl">Director Carl Th.Schrembs</persName></p>
               <p>Munich 0 51</p>
               <p>Haralaching 3</p>
            </div>
            <div rend="body">
               <p>Dear <persName key="schrembsCarl">Mr. Schrembs</persName>!</p>
               <p>I would like to thank you for your kind words about my <persName key="lili">Lili
                     Elbe</persName> book.</p>
               <p>Your letter isn’t the first one asking questions and demanding answers. This makes
                  me realize how important it was for me to publish this book.</p>
               <p>One of your questions is whether <persName key="lili">Lili</persName> really died
                  due to heart failure. Well, <persName key="warnekros">Professor
                     Warnekros</persName> doesn’t have anything to hide: <persName key="lili"
                     >Lili's</persName> death had nothing to do with the necessary procedures
                  performed on her by <persName key="warnekros">W.</persName> An old kidney disease,
                  that <persName key="wegenerE">Einar (Andreas)</persName> had suffered from many
                  years ago, suddenly resurfaced. This was a couple of weeks after the last,
                  successful operation.- Kidney diseases take their toll on the heart, and the heart
                  becomes overworked…</p>
               <p>There is no reason to question <persName key="warnekros">Professor
                     Warnerkros'</persName> statements. Besides, he wasn’t in <placeName
                        key="dresden">Dresden</placeName>, but in <placeName key="franceSouth"
                           >southern France</placeName>, when the old kidney disease suddenly arose after the
                  successful last operation. At the moment I am uncertain whether <persName
                     key="lili">Lili</persName> or <persName key="sparreAn">Andreas</persName> ever
                  even mentioned the kidney disesase to <persName key="warnekros">Professor
                     W.</persName>; I dont think so. <persName key="lili">Lili</persName> never even
                  mentioned to me, a person that she confessed everything to, that <persName
                     key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> ever had kidney problems.</p>
               <p><persName key="lili">Lili</persName> never had cancer. That's a myth. Considering
                  how we are as humans, it's understandable, that enviers of <persName
                     key="warnekros">Professor W.</persName> would want to meddle in his affairs.
                  Without doubt, <persName key="wegenerE">Einar</persName> would have died many
                  months earlier, had it not been for <persName key="warnekros">Professor
                     W.'s</persName> interference. Besides, <persName key="warnekros">Professor
                     W.</persName> read my manuscript in its entirety before it was printed, and
                  literally changed less than 30 lines.-</p>
               <p>I will happily stay in contact with you. Each one of your letters will recieve a
                  clear reply. In 2 to 3 years, I would like to write a novel based on my <persName
                     key="lili">Lili Elbe</persName> book, which views this problematic issue of
                  "soul and body" (if I may phrase it like that) from a purley poetic point of view.
                  I still own other unpublished documents from <pb style="page" n="2"/><persName key="lili">Lili
                     Elbe</persName>, that I will work on at a later point in time.</p>
               <p>You were so kind to me in <placeName key="">Munich</placeName>. I'm sure I will
                  travel there in the near future. I will give you an advance notice when I do.</p>
               <p>You also mentioned my wife, who you met through my book...? This must be a
                  mistake. I never mentioned <persName key="garlandM">my wife</persName>. She
                  frequently corresponded with <persName key="lili">Lili</persName>, and talked to
                  her often. But she is not mentioned in the book. Perhaps you are confusing her
                  with my daughter, <persName key="ruth">Ruth</persName>, <persName key="lili"
                     >Lili's</persName> only student?</p>
               <p>Naturally, I regard our correspondence as confidential.</p>
               <p>By the way, what does "director of M.T.A.G." mean?</p>
               <p>Best wishes,</p>
               <signed>Yours Sincerely</signed>
               <postscript>
                  <p>It might be of interest to you, that my book will be published in <placeName
                        key="london">London</placeName>, <placeName key="newYork">New
                        York</placeName>, <placeName key="budapest">Budapest</placeName>, <placeName
                        key="paris">Paris</placeName>, <placeName key="belgrad"
                     >Belgrade</placeName>, etc. in a few months. If you happen to find any
                     conversation about it in Munich's newspapers, please send them to me.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
