<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="LEDA_ODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rendition="lilielbe.org/narrative/editions/A1.html"
    xml:base="https://gitlab.com/ctsdh/lili-elbe-code/raw/master/XSLT_sandbox/EditionNumbering/input/A1.xml">
    <!-- insert correct URLs, above, for your text -->
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title> Lili Elvenæs, alias Ejnar Wegener, er afgaaet ved Døden. <hi rend="italics">En tragisk Afslutning paa en fantastisk Livsskæbne.</hi> (<date>September
                        1931</date>)</title>
                <title type="alternative">Lili Elvenes, alias Einar Wegener, has passed away.
                    <hi rend="italics">A Tragic End to a Fantastic Life.</hi> (<date>September 1931</date>)</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="bastJørgen" role="AUT"
                        >Jørgen Bast</persName>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Translation completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="mo" role="TRL"
                        >Marianne Ølholm</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Translation reviewed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="mo"
                        >Marianne Ølholm</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by </resp>
                    <persName ref="mo">Marianne Ølholm</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="co">Colin O'Connell</persName>
                    <persName ref="swv">Susan VanDerveer</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance and/or XML proofing completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="co">Colin O'Connell</persName>
                    <persName ref="ccm">Caroline McCraw</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>XML transformed into HTML
                        <date><!-- exact transformation date generated during transformation; leave this one alone --></date>
                        by</resp>
                    <persName ref="rjp">Rebecca J. Parker</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>HTML proofing completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""><!-- Insert Proofers name and initials in @ref--></persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Images prepared by</resp>
                    <persName ref="mg">Matthew Gallagher</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Loyola University Chicago Libraries</sponsor>
                <sponsor>Loyola's Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Lili Elbe Digital Archive</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when="2019-07-06">July 6th, 2019</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName select="source">Ernst Harthern Archives,
                        Arbetarrörelsens Arkiv och Bibliotek (Swedish Labour Movement's Archives and
                        Library)</orgName> in <placeName>Huddinge, Sweden</placeName>.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc source="Periodical" xml:lang="dan">
                <p>A clipping affixed to a thin piece of paper in the EHSA shows four columns, no photographs, with two holes punched at the bottom of the middle columns; the publication information is handwritten in black ink across the top, and some stains (possibly water damage) obscure some parts of the article</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy source="https://arc-staging.dh.tamu.edu/index.php/Submitting_RDF">
                    <category source="collex" xml:id="discipline">
                        <catDesc>History/Gender Studies</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category source="collex" xml:id="genre">
                        <catDesc>Essay/Nonfiction</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category source="collex" xml:id="text">
                        <catDesc>https://gitlab.com/ctsdh/lili-elbe-code/raw/master/XSLT_sandbox/plainText/output/filename.txt</catDesc><!-- insert correct URL -->
                    </category>
                    <category source="dc" xml:id="date">
                        <catDesc>
                            <![CDATA[<dc:date>date metadata</dc:date>]]><!-- Do not forget to change the text between the dc:date tags AND include the <![CDATA[ before the dc:date tage and ]]> after it. -->
                        </catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category source="dcterms" xml:id="isPartOf" xml:lang="dan">
                        <catDesc>Lili Elvenæs, alias Ejnar Wegener, er afgaaet ved Døden. <hi rend="italics">En tragisk Afslutning paa en fantastisk Livsskæbne.</hi></catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category source="dcterms" xml:id="isPartOf_trans" xml:lang="eng">
                        <catDesc>Lili Elvenes, alias Einar Wegener, has passed away. <hi rend="italics">A Tragic End to a Fantastic Life.</hi></catDesc>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <!-- Verify with Rebecca that your document does not need additional editorial declarations. Most of the editions have additional children elements here (i.e. segmentation) -->
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>We have removed the hyphenation that appears in the printed text during
                        digitization and encoding. Original hyphenation can be consulted in the facsimile
                        images.</p>
                </hyphenation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="original">
                <div rend="head" style="periodical">
                    <p>
                        <title>Berlingske Titende</title>
                        <date when="1932-09-14"></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div rend="headlines">
                    <list>
                        <item rend="primary">
                            <persName>Lili Elvenæs</persName>, alias <persName>Ejnar Wegener</persName>, er afgaaet ved Døden.
                        </item>
                        <item> 
                            <hi rend="italics">En tragisk Afslutning paa en fantastisk Livsskæbne.</hi>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div rend="body">
                    <p>Det vakte for et lille Aars tid siden Opsigt Verden over, baade i 
                        videnskabelige Kredse og der, hvor man søger Sensation, at 
                        Maleren <persName key="wegenerE">Ejnar Wegener</persName> paa en <placeName key="womensClinic">Klinik</placeName> i <placeName key="dresden">Dresden</placeName> var blevet 
                        underkastet en Operation, der havde forvandlet ham fra Mand til 
                        Kvinde.</p>
                    <p>Oprindelig troede man i alt Fald herhjemme, at det var et af 
                        disse fantastiske Rygter, der opstaar, uden at nogen véd hvordan – 
                        men en skønne Dag kom den mærkelige Bekræftelse paa Rygtet: 
                        <persName key="lili">Lili Elvenæs</persName>, en meget smuk og livlig Dame, dukkede op i 
                        <placeName key="copenhagen">København</placeName> og udstillede sit tidligere Jegs, <persName key="wegenerE">Ejnar Wegeners</persName>, 
                        Billeder i <placeName key="haslundsHus">“Ole Haslunds Hus”</placeName>.</p>
                    <p>Operationen, der havde fundet Sted i <placeName key="dresden">Dresden</placeName>, var Udgangen 
                        paa mange Aars Lidelser og Kampe.</p>
                    <p>Alle Københavnere af den ældre Aargang husker jo den unge 
                        <persName key="wegenerE"><hi rend="italics">Ejnar Wegener</hi></persName>, en lys, veg køn Fyr, der snarere lignede 
                        et kønt Pigebarn i Herreklæder end et Mandfolk.</p>
                    <p>Som hans Ydre var ogsaa hans Talent, vegt og kvindeligt, 
                        men Talent var der, hvad navnlig hans mange Bybilleder fra hans 
                        elskede <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName> bærer Vidne om.</p>
                    <p><persName key="wegenerE">Ejnar Wegeners</persName> Lykke var, at han traf sin Hustru, den 
                        berømte Malerinde <persName key="wegenerG"><hi rend="italics">Gerda Wegener</hi></persName>. Han fik her en ven for Livet, 
                        et Menneske, der forstod ham og hans ulykkelige Natur. De rejste 
                        til <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName> sammen, de kom til at høre til <placeName key="montparnasse">Montparnasse’s</placeName> kendte 
                        Kunstnere, de tjente Penge, og navnlig <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda Wegener</persName> fik 
                        efterhaanden meget store Indtægter baade gennem sine Malerier og 
                        sine glimrende Reklametegninger.</p>
                    <p>Trods Medgangen var <persName key="wegenerE">Ejnar Wegener</persName> et dybt ulykkeligt 
                        Menneske. Han var Mand af Skikkelse og Navn, men han følte sig 
                        helt som Kvinde, og efterhaanden som Aarene gik, drev hans 
                        særlige Kompleks ham næsten til Vanvidets og Selvmordets Rand.</p>
                    <p>I Aarenes Løb søgte han Raad og Hjælp mange Steder, men 
                        ingen kunde hjælpe ham, indtil den berømte tyske Kirurg, 
                        <persName key="warnekros">Professor Warnekros</persName> i <placeName key="dresden">Dresden</placeName> gav ham et Haab. Han paatog sig 
                        den vanskelige Operation – for at hjælpe et ulykkeligt Menneske men 
                        vel ogsaa for at gøre et videnskabeligt Eksperiment der aldrig 
                        før var forsøgt. Her var Tale om en slags Vivisektion, hvor Ofret 
                        meldte sig frivilligt.</p>
                    <p>Det hele kunne dog ikke ordnes med een Operation. Efter sit 
                        korte Ophold i <placeName key="copenhagen">København</placeName> maatte <persName key="lili">Lili Elvenæs</persName> vende tilbage til 
                        <anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="2"/><placeName key="womensClinic">Klinikken</placeName><anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="1"/><note type="translator" source="mo" corresp="comment_2">Here a punch hole in the clipping obscures some letters. Likely the word is Klinikken (the clinic)</note>for at underkaste 
                        sig endnu et Par Operationer. Disse syntes at være forløbet heldigt, 
                        men saa viste det sig, at den Opererede led af en indvendig Lidelse, 
                        vistnok Kræft, der udviklede sig med forfærdende Hast – og nu er 
                        <persName key="lili">Lili Elvenæs</persName> altsaa død. Naturen lod sig alligevel ikke trodse.</p>
                    <p>Tilfældet <persName key="wegenerE">EjnarWegener</persName>-<persName key="lili">LiliElvenæs</persName> vil sikkert i Fremtiden 
                        staa som en psykologisk Gaade-og vil ulvivlsom 
                        mange, mange Gange blive gjort til genstrand for for videnskabelig 
                        Drøftelse. Heri vil utvivlsom en Selvbiografi, som <persName key="lili">LiliElvenæs</persName>
                        havde afsluttet umiddelbart før sin Død, komme til at spille en stor 
                        Polle. Det mærkeligste Afsnit af den er bygget over 
                        Dagbogsoptegnelser fra Opholdet paa <placeName key="womensClinic">Klinikken</placeName>, saaledes at 
                        Dagbogen først er ført af <persName key="wegenerE">EjnarWegener</persName>, derefter af det neutrale 
                        Væsen, der eksisterede, men Operation blev foretaget og endelig 
                        af en ny Kvinde <persName key="lili">LiliElvenæs</persName>.</p>
                    <p>Det psykologisk mest ejendommelige er det, at <persName key="lili">LiliElvenæs</persName>
                        slet ikke har nogen fornemmelse af <persName key="wegenerE">EjnarWegeners</persName>Eksistens, men 
                        regner ham for et afdølt Væsen.</p>
                    <p>Under sit Ophold i <placeName key="copenhagen">Københaven</placeName>sagde <persName key="lili">LiliElvenæs</persName>:</p>
                    <p><persName key="wegenerE">EjnarWegener</persName>kunne male. Jeg har desværre ingen 
                        Talenter. Jeg vil helst sy.</p>
                    <p>Hun var slet ikke klar over det tragikomiske i en replik som denne:</p>
                    <p><persName key="wegenerE">EjnarWegener</persName>var en underlig Fryr. Han gik baade i Teatret 
                        og paa Caféer lige før jeg blev opereret.</p>
                    <p>Det var i fuld Overensstemmelse med sin Hustru, Fru <persName key="wegenerG">GerdaWegener</persName>, 
                        at han lod sig underkaste Operation-men der opstod 
                        efter den et ganske mærkeligt juridisk Problem: Hvordan skulle 
                        ægteskabet opløses? Sagen blev <anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="3"/>indbragt<anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="3"/><note type="translator" source="mo" corresp="comment_3">Here a punch hole in the clipping obscures some letters. Likely the complete word is <hi rend="italics">indbragt</hi> (brought).</note>for det 
                        <persName>danske Jutitsministerium</persName>, men man gennemsøgte forgæves 
                        samtlige mærkelige ægteskabeligt-juridiske Porlemer i Verden 
                        uden at finde noget Tilfælde, der mindede om dette. Det endte da 
                        med, at man ganske simpelt erklærede Ægteskabet for ugyldigt.</p>
                    <p>Det trofaste Venskab mellem <persName key="lili">LiliElvenæs</persName> og <persName key="wegenerG">GerdaWegener</persName> 
                        vedvarer til det sidste – og havde <persName key="lili">LiliElvenæs</persName>rejst sig 
                        fra Sygelejet, skulde hun være rejst til <placeName key="morocco">Marokko</placeName> for at besøge 
                        <persName key="wegenerG">GerdaWegener</persName>, der lever dèr i lykkeligt Ægteskab med en 
                        <persName>italiensk officer.</persName></p>
                    <p>Naar man har kendt <persName key="wegenerE">EjnarWegener</persName> i de yngre Aar, staar man 
                        underligt forvirret ved hans Død. Skal man sørge over, at der er sat 
                        Punktum for en umulig Livsskæbne? Skal man mindes <persName key="wegenerE">EjnarWegener</persName> 
                        med det blide, vemodige Væsen, eller den 
                        temperamentsfulde <persName key="lili">Lili Elvenæs</persName>? Det er slet ikke til at sige. Dette 
                        underlige væsens Gaade rækker ud over Døden.</p>
                    <signed><persName key="bastJørgen">JørgenBast</persName></signed>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="translation">
                <div rend="head" style="periodical">
                    <p>
                        <title>Berlingske Tidende</title>
                        <date when="1931-09-14"></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div rend="headlines">
                    <list>
                        <item rend="primary">
                            Lili Elvenes, alias Einar Wegener, has passed away.
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italics">A Tragic End to a Fantastic Life.</hi>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div rend="body">
                    <p>Just under a year ago, it created a sensation across the world, both 
                        in scientific circles and in places where sensation is sought, that the 
                        painter <persName key="wegenerE">Einar Wegener</persName> had undergone an operation at a <placeName key="womensClinic">clinic</placeName> in 
                        <placeName key="dresden">Dresden</placeName> that had transformed him from a man into a woman.</p>
                    <p>Originally it was believed, at least in this country, that it was 
                        one of these wild rumours that spring up without anybody knowing 
                        how – but one day the extraordinary confirmation of the rumour 
                        came: <persName key="lili">Lili Elvenes</persName>, a very beautiful and lively lady, appeared in 
                        <placeName key="copenhagen">Copenhagen</placeName> and exhibited the paintings by her former self, <persName key="wegenerE">Einar 
                            Wegener</persName>, in <placeName key="haslundsHus">“Ole Haslund’s House”</placeName>.</p>
                    <p>The operation that had taken place in <placeName>Dresden</placeName> was the 
                        outcome of many years of suffering and struggling.</p>
                    <p>All Copenhageners of the older years remember the young 
                        <persName key="wegenerE">Einar Wegener</persName>, a blond, soft pretty fellow who looked like 
                        a pretty girl in men’s clothes rather than a man.</p>
                    <p>As his appearance was also his talent, passive and feminine, 
                        but talent there was, as particularly his many city scenes from his 
                        beloved <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName> bear witness to.</p>
                    <p>It was <persName>Einar Wegener’s</persName> good fortune that he met his wife, 
                        the famous painter <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda Wegener</persName>. Here he acquired a friend for 
                        life, a person who understood him and his <anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="1"/>unfortunate<anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="1"/><note type="translator" source="mo" corresp="comment_1">Ulykkelig also means "unhappy".</note> nature. They 
                        travelled to <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName> together, they got to be among the famous artists 
                        of <placeName key="montparnasse">Montparnasse</placeName>, they made money, and particularly <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda 
                        Wegener</persName> eventually had very large earnings, both from her 
                        paintings and her excellent commercial art.</p>   
                    <p>In spite of his success <persName key="wegenerE">Einar Wegener</persName> was a deeply unhappy 
                        person. He was a man by physical stature and name but he felt 
                        entirely like a woman and as the years passed, his particular 
                        complex almost drove him to the verge of madness and suicide.</p>
                    <p>Over the years, he sought advice and help in many places, 
                        but no one could help him until the famous German surgeon 
                        <persName key="warnekros">Professor Warnekros</persName> in <placeName key="dresden">Dresden</placeName> gave him a hope. He took on the 
                        difficult operation – to help an unhappy person but probably also to 
                        do a scientific experiment that had never been attempted before. 
                        This was a kind of vivisection where the victim volunteered.</p>
                    <p>Everything could not be taken care of in one operation 
                        however. After her short stay in <placeName key="copenhagen">Copenhagen</placeName>, <persName key="lili">Lili Elvenes</persName> had to 
                        return to the <placeName key="womensClinic">clinic</placeName> in order to undergo several further operations. These seem to have been successful but 
                        then it turned out that the patient suffered from an internal disorder, 
                        probably cancer, that developed at a terrifying speed – and now 
                        <persName key="lili">Lili Elvenes</persName> is dead. Nature was not to be defied after all.</p>
                    <p>The case of <persName key="wegenerE">EinarWegener</persName>- <persName key="lili">LiliElvenes</persName>will probably stand 
                        as a psychological-physiological mystery in the future - and no 
                        doubt it will be made the subject of scientific discussion in many, 
                        many times. In these, an autobigraphy that <persName key="lili">LiliElvenes</persName>had 
                        finished immediately before her death will no doubt play an 
                        important role. The most extraordinary part of it is based on diary 
                        entries from the stay at <placeName key="womensClinic">the clinic</placeName> so so that at first, the diary is kept by 
                        <persName key="wegenerE">EinarWegener</persName>, then by the neutral being, and finally by a new 
                        woman <persName key="lili">LiliElvenes</persName>.</p>
                    <p>Most psychologically remarkable is that <persName key="lili">LiliElvenes</persName> has no 
                        sense at all of <persName key= "wegenerE">EinerWegener's</persName> existence but regards him as a 
                        deceased being.</p>
                    <p>During her stay in <placeName key= "copenhagen">Copenhagen</placeName>, <persName key= "lili">LiliElvenes</persName>  said:</p>
                    <p>- <persName key="wegenerE">Einar Wegener</persName> could paint. Unfortunately, I have no
                        talents. I would rather sew.</p>
                    <p>She was completely unaware of the tragicomical in a remark 
                        like this:</p>
                    <p>- <persName key="wegenerE">EinarWegener</persName>was a strange guy. He both went to the 
                        theatre and to cafés just before I had surgery.</p>
                    <p>It was a complete agreement with his wife, <persName key="wegenerG">Mrs. Gerda Wegener</persName>, 
                        that he underwent the operation- but afterwords a quite 
                        extraordinary legal problem arose: how was the marriage to be 
                        dissolved? The case was brought before the 
                        <persName>Danish Ministry of Justice</persName> but all the extraordinary problems of 
                        marriage law in the world were searched through without finding 
                        any case resembling this. Eventually the marriage was quite simply 
                        declared invalid.</p>
                    <p>The faithful friendship between <persName key="lili">LiliElvens</persName> and <persName key="wegenerG">GerdaWegener</persName> 
                        lasted to the end- and had <persName key="lili">LiliElvenes</persName> risen from her 
                        sickbed, she would have travelled to <placeName key="morocco">Morocco</placeName> to visit <persName key="wegenerG">GerdaWegener</persName>, 
                        who lives there in a happy marriage to an <persName>Italian officer.</persName></p>
                    <p>Having known <persName key="wegenerE">EinareWegener</persName> in his younger years, one is 
                        strangely confused at his death. Is one to mourn that an impossible 
                        fate is terminated? Is one to remember <persName key="wegenerE">EinarWegener</persName> with the 
                        gentle melancholy nature or tempermental <persName key="lili">LiliElvenes</persName>? 
                        No one can say. The mystery of this extraordinary being extends beyond death,</p>
                    <signed><persName key="bastJørgen">JørgenBast</persName></signed>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>