<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="LEDA%20XML/LEDA_ODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rendition="lilielbe.org/narrative/editions/A1.html"
    xml:base="https://gitlab.com/ctsdh/lili-elbe-code/raw/master/XSLT_sandbox/EditionNumbering/input/A1.xml">
    <!-- insert correct URLs, above, for your text -->
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title><hi rend="bold">Kønskarakteren og dens Svingninger</hi><hi rend="italics">– Prof. Knud Sand udtaler sig om abnorme Kønstilstande hos Mennesker.</hi>(<date>Marts
                        1931</date>)</title>
                <title type="alternative"><hi rend="bold">Sexual Character and its Variations</hi><hi rend="italics">– Prof. Knud Sand Speaks About Abnormal Sexual States in Humans.</hi>(<date>March 1931</date>)</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="louLou" role="AUT"
                        >Loulou Lassen</persName>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Translation completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="mo" role="TRL"
                        >Marianne Ølholm</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Translation reviewed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="mo"
                        >Marianne Ølholm</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by </resp>
                    <persName ref="mo">Marianne Ølholm</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="co">Colin O'Connell</persName>
                    <persName ref="bt">Brenda Torres</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance and/or XML proofing completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="co">Colin O'Connell</persName>
                    <persName ref="ccm">Caroline McCraw</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>XML transformed into HTML
                        <date><!-- exact transformation date generated during transformation; leave this one alone --></date>
                        by</resp>
                    <persName ref="rjp">Rebecca J. Parker</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>HTML proofing completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""><!-- Insert Proofers name and initials in @ref--></persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Images prepared by</resp>
                    <persName ref="mg">Matthew Gallagher</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Loyola University Chicago Libraries</sponsor>
                <sponsor>Loyola's Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Lili Elbe Digital Archive</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when="2019-07-06">July 6th, 2019</date>
                <availability>
                    <p select="source">Private Collection.</p> <!-- OR --> <p select="source">Royal Danish Library</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc source="Periodical" xml:lang="dan">
                <p></p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <!-- Consult Dr. Caughie, Emily, or Rebecca to verify metadata specifics -->
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy source="https://arc-staging.dh.tamu.edu/index.php/Submitting_RDF">
                    <category source="collex" xml:id="discipline">
                        <catDesc>History/Gender Studies</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category source="collex" xml:id="genre">
                        <catDesc>Essay/Nonfiction</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category source="dcterms" xml:id="isPartOf" xml:lang="dan">
                        <catDesc>Politiken</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category source="dcterms" xml:id="isPartOf_trans" xml:lang="eng">
                        <catDesc>Politiken</catDesc>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <!-- Verify with Rebecca that your document does not need additional editorial declarations. Most of the editions have additional children elements here (i.e. segmentation) -->
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>We have removed the hyphenation that appears in the printed text during
                        digitization and encoding. Original hyphenation can be consulted in the facsimile
                        images.</p>
                </hyphenation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="original">
                <div rend="head" style="periodical">
                    <p>
                        <title>Politiken</title>
                        <date when="1931-03-01">søndag den 1. Marts 1931</date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div rend="headlines">
                    <!-- Prof. Knud Sand not included in the prosopography -CO 12/01/19 -->
                    <list>
                        <item rend="primary"><hi rend="bold">Kønskarakteren og dens Svingninger</hi></item>
                        <item><hi rend="italics">– Prof. Knud Sand udtaler sig om abnorme Kønstilstande hos Mennesker.</hi></item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div rend="body">
                    <p>I Anledning af vor Meddelelse i Gaar om en kendt Kunstners 
                        omskiftede Tilværelse har vi henvendt os til vor hjemlige 
                        Seksualbiolog, <persName>Professor <hi rend="italics">Knud Sand</hi></persName>, hvis Forskninger over 
                        Kønsomdannelser og Kønshormoner i det hele er Offentligheden 
                        bekendt, og spurgt ham, om saadanne Forhold er almindelige, og 
                        hvorledes Udsigterne er til at hjælpe de Mennesker, der i kønslig 
                        Henseende afviger fra det normale.</p>
                    <p>Under vor Samtale udtalte <persName>Professoren</persName> bl. a. følgende:</p>
                    <p>– Hidtil har jeg væsentlig fulgt det Princip hverken at skrive eller 
                        udtale mig i Pressen om disse Forhold og Forskninger, der vel næppe 
                        endnu er helt saa langt fremme, at de mere indgaaende bør 
                        forelægges for Offentligheden; i de senere Aar har jeg dog Indtryk 
                        af, at Folk er blevet mere lydhøre for en rigtig Forstaaelse af disse 
                        Problemer, end Tilfældet var blot for en seksten-sytten Aar siden, da 
                        jeg begyndte mine Arbejder paa dette Felt. Det er da at haabe, at 
                        ogsaa det omtalte Tilfælde vil møde Forstaaelse, og da 
                        vedkommende Patient nu selv – formentlig for at faa Ro om Sagen
                        – har ønsket denne offentliggjort og dermed forhaabentlig skrinlagt, 
                        skal jeg, ganske særlig ogsaa for at berolige Lidelsesfæller af hende, 
                        give Deres Blad, som har bragt Meddelelsen, nogle Oplysninger, 
                        idet jeg dog af forskellige Grunde ikke ønsker at udtale mig om selve 
                        det omhandlede Tilfælde.</p>
                    <p>Abnorme Kønstilstande hos Mennesker <hi rend="italics">er i Virkeligheden 
                        langt hyppigere</hi>, end Folk tror. Ikke alene udgør Afvigelserne i selve 
                        Kønsdriften, de saakaldte psykoseksuelle Abnormiteter som
                        Homoseksualisme, Biseksualisme o. a. et ikke ringe Procenttal, men 
                        selv saadanne Tilfælde, hvor det ogsaa drejer sig om udtalte 
                        legemlige Abnormiteter i Henseende til hele Kønssystemets 
                        Udvikling, er ikke Sjældenheder. Selv har jeg herhjemme Kendskab 
                        til en Række af dem.</p>
                    <p>I det hele forholder det sig saaledes, at <hi rend="italics">maaske kun ganske faa 
                        af os kan karakteriseres som absolut Mænd eller Kvinder</hi>; den 
                        Kyndige vil oftest kunne paavise et mere eller mindre udtalt Islæt af 
                        det modsatte Køn, i legemlig eller psykisk Henseende, svagere eller 
                        stærkere prægede Mellemstadier mellem de to Yderpunkter.</p>
                    <p>For langt de flestes Vedkommende er det jo lykkeligvis 
                        saaledes, at dette slet ikke kommer til synligt Udtryk eller faar 
                        Betydning for Individets Liv eller sociale Indstilling … Kun naar 
                        Abnormiteten er stærkere, indtræder Kalamiteter af den ene eller 
                        anden Art.</p>
                    <p>Misèren stammer i de mest abnorme Tilfælde, de saakaldte 
                        <hi rend="italics">hermafroditiske</hi>, oftest derfra, at Individets Kønsbestemmelse ved 
                        Fødslen er meget vanskelig og Fejltagelser derfor sker baade fra 
                        Jordemoderens og Lægens Side – først senere aabenbarer de rette 
                        Forhold sig.</p>
                    <p>En Del af disse Mennesker kommer i Konflikt med de civile 
                        eller strafferetlige Love, det er dog lykkeligvis de færreste. Langt 
                        flere lever en ensom Tilværelse i Skyhed for deres Medmennesker 
                        af Angst for, at Sandheden skal afsløres, og i en stadig Kamp for at 
                        dække den. Alt i alt hører de kønsligt Abnorme <hi rend="italics">til de ulykkeligste 
                        blandt Mennesker</hi>, og der ligger en stor Opgave for 
                        Lægevidenskaben i at hjælpe dem.</p>
                    <p>I disse tragiske Forhold for denne Menneskegruppe er der dog 
                        i de sidste Decennier indtraadt en betydelig Ændring til det bedre. 
                        Ikke alene er – som allerede nævnt – den almene Forstaaelse af, at 
                        det drejer sig om medfødte Abnormiteter, voksende, hvilket ogsaa 
                        giver sig Udslag i Lovgivning og Bestemmelser over for disse 
                        Menneskers sociale Stilling og derigennem i en Lettelse af deres 
                        Kaar, men ogsaa Biologien og Lægevidenskaben har i den sidste 
                        Menneskealder klarlagt mange af de herhen hørende Problemer.</p>
                    <p>Baade fra Udlandet og herhjemme fra kender man da ogsaa 
                        Tilfælde, hvor man gennem operative og andre Behandlinger har 
                        kunnet hjælpe de seksuelt abnorme, og gennem vor fortsatte 
                        Forskning – bl. a. over Seksualhormonernes nærmere Forhold – er 
                        der berettiget Haab om at naa yderligere frem, selv om man ikke tør 
                        fæste for megen Lid til de sensationelle Meddelelser, der fra Tid til 
                        anden fremkommer om Vidunderkure paa dette som paa andre 
                        Omraader.</p>
                    <p>Hvad jeg imidlertid særlig føler Trang til at pointere, er, at det,
                        som disse ulykkeligt stillede Mennesker frem for alt trænger til, er 
                        Forstaaelse og Fred for al nyfigen og sensationel Omtale, det være 
                        sig Mand og Mand imellem eller offentligt.</p>
                    <p>Andre medfødte Abnormiteter som Hareskaar, Klumpfødder 
                        eller lignende, giver dog ingen Anledning dertil. Var der da ikke 
                        endnu mere Grund til at skaane disse af Skæbnen saa haardt ramte 
                        Individer, de seksuelt Abnorme?</p>
                    <p>Ikke alene det omtalte Tilfælde bør nu have Fred. Men alle
                        Spørgsmaal inden for Seksuallæren burde offentlig behandles med 
                        en endog særlig Forstaaelse, Værdighed og Objektivitet … Det 
                        vilde, slutter <persName>Prof. Sand</persName> sine Udtalelser, baade lette Tilværelsen for 
                        den omtalte ulykkelige Menneskegruppe og det videnskabelige 
                        Arbejde med disse Problemer.</p>
                    <signed><persName key="louLou"><hi rend="italics">Fru Loulou</hi></persName></signed>
                    <postscript><p><persName>Billedtekst:
                        Prof. Dr. med. Knud Sand.</persName></p>
                    </postscript>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="translation">
                <div rend="head" style="periodical">
                    <p>
                        <title>Politiken</title>
                        <date when="1931-03-01">1 March 1931</date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div rend="headlines">
                    <!-- Prof. Knud Sand not included in the prosopography -CO 12/01/19 -->
                    <list>
                        <item rend="primary"><hi rend="bold">Sexual Character and its Variations</hi></item>
                        <item><hi rend="italics">– Prof. Knud Sand Speaks About Abnormal Sexual States in Humans.</hi></item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div rend="body">
                    <p>On the occasion of our announcement yesterday, about the changed 
                        existence of a well-known artist we have approached our domestic
                        sexual biologist, <persName>Professor <hi rend="italics">Knud Sand</hi></persName>, whose researches into 
                        gender transformations and sexual hormones in general is familiar 
                        to the public, and asked him if such conditions are common and 
                        how the prospects are of helping those people who sexually differ 
                        from the normal.</p>
                    <p>During our conversation <persName>the Professor</persName> made the following 
                        statement among others:</p>
                    <p>– Till now, I have primarily followed the principle of neither
                        writing nor speaking in the press about these conditions and 
                        researches that are hardly quite so far advanced yet that they ought 
                        to be presented in greater detail to the public; in recent years, I do
                        however have the impression that people have become more open 
                        to a real understanding of these problems than was the case only 
                        sixteen or seventeen years ago when I started my works in this 
                        field. It is to be hoped that also the case in question will meet with 
                        understanding, and as the patient herself – presumably to lay the 
                        matter to rest – has wanted this made public and thus hopefully
                        dropped, I will, in particular to reassure her fellow sufferers, give 
                        your paper, which has brought the announcement, some 
                        information, although for various reasons I do not want to address
                        the actual case at issue.</p>
                    <p>Abnormal gender states in humans <hi rend="italics">are in fact much more 
                        frequent</hi> than people think. Not only do the deviations in the sex
                        drive itself, the so-called psychosexual abnormalities such as
                        homosexuality, bisexuality et al. constitute a not small 
                        percentage, but even such cases where it is also a question of
                        distinct physical abnormalities with regard to the development of 
                        the whole sexual system are not rare. I myself know of a number of
                        them in this country.</p>
                    <p>On the whole, the reality is that <hi rend="italics">perhaps only very few of us
                        can be characterized as absolute men or women</hi>; the expert will
                        most often be able to point out a more or less pronounced element 
                        of the opposite sex, physically or mentally, weakly or strongly 
                        marked intermediate stages between the two extremes.</p>
                    <p>For most people this is fortunately not at all visibly manifest
                        nor of importance to the life or social approach of the individual … 
                        Only when the abnormality is stronger, do calamities of one kind 
                        or another occur.</p>
                    <p>In the most abnormal cases, the so-called <hi rend="italics">hermaphrodite</hi>, the 
                        problem stems from the fact that the determination of the sex of the
                        individual at birth is very difficult and for that reason mistakes 
                        occur, both on the part of the midwife and the doctor – only later 
                        do the true circumstances reveal themselves.</p>
                    <p>Some of these people come into conflict with the civil or 
                        criminal laws, but happily this is a minority. A far greater number
                        live a lonely existence in shyness of their fellow human beings
                        from fear that the truth will be revealed and in a constant struggle
                        to cover it. All in all, the sexually abnormal belong to <hi rend="italics">the 
                        unhappiest of people</hi>, and for medical science a great challenge lies
                        in helping them.</p>
                    <p>In these tragic conditions for this group of people a 
                        considerable change for the better has occurred in the last decades.
                        Not only – as already mentioned – is the general understanding of 
                        the fact that it is a question of congenital abnormalities growing,
                        which is also reflected in legislation and regulations with regard to 
                        the social position of these people and in this way in a relief of 
                        their conditions, but also biology and medical science have 
                        clarified many of the problems pertaining to this in the last 
                        generation.</p>
                    <p>Both from abroad and in this country, cases are known where 
                        it has been possible through surgical and other treatments to help 
                        the sexually abnormal, and through our continued research – 
                        among other things into the more specific details of the sexual 
                        hormones– there is legitimate hope of making further progress, 
                        even if too much confidence should not be placed in the
                        sensational announcements that from time to time appear about
                        miracle cures in this as well as in other areas.</p>
                    <p>What I particularly want to emphasize, however, is that what 
                        these unfortunate people need above all is understanding and to
                        have some peace from all prying and sensational discussion, be it 
                        among the general population or publicly.</p>
                    <p>Other congenital abnormalities such as a harelip, clubfeet, or
                        the like give no cause for this. Is there then not even more reason
                        to spare these, by fate, so severely affected individuals, the 
                        sexually abnormal?</p>
                    <p>Not only the said case should be left in peace now. But all 
                        questions within sexology should be treated publicly with 
                        particular understanding, dignity and objectivity … That would, 
                        <persName>Prof. Sand</persName> ends his remarks, make life for the said unhappy group
                        of people and the scientific work on these problems easier.</p>
                    <signed><persName key="louLou"><hi rend="italics">Mrs. Loulou</hi></persName></signed>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Caption:
                        <persName>Prof. and Doctor of medical science Knud Sand.</persName></p>
                    </postscript>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
