<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="LEDA_ODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
    rendition="lilielbe.org/context/letters/1933-10-22GWegenerKnudsen.html"
    xml:base="https://gitlab.com/ctsdh/lili-elbe-code/blob/master/XSLT_sandbox/readingViews/input/letters/19331022GWegenerKnudsen.xml">
   
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
               
                
                <title>
                    <date when="1933-10-22">October 22, 1933</date> Letter to <persName key="knudsenP">Paul Knudsen</persName>
                </title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="wegenerG" role="AUT">Gerda Wegener</persName>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Translation completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="mo" role="TRL"
                        >Marianne Ølholm</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Translation reviewed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="plc">Pamela L. Caughie</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by </resp>
                    <persName ref="mo" role="TRL"
                        >Marianne Ølholm</persName>
                </respStmt>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="drr">Danielle Richards</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance and/or XML proofing completed by</resp>
                    <persName><!-- Has not yet been proofed--></persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>XML transformed into HTML
                        <date>
                       <!-- exact transformation date generated during transformation; leave this one alone --></date>
                        by</resp>
                    <persName ref="rjp">Rebecca J. Parker</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>HTML proofing completed by</resp>
                    <persName><!-- Has not yet been proofed--></persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Images prepared by</resp>
                    <persName ref="mg">Matthew Gallagher</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Loyola University Chicago Libraries</sponsor>
                <sponsor>Loyola's Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Lili Elbe Digital Archive</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when="2019-07-06">July 6th, 2019</date>
                <!-- Consult Dr. Caughie, Emily, or Rebecca to verify which example to follow according to your text -->
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName select="source">Ernst Harthern Archives,
                        Arbetarrörelsens Arkiv och Bibliotek (Swedish Labour Movement's Archives and
                        Library)</orgName> in <placeName>Huddinge, Sweden</placeName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc source="Manuscript" xml:lang="dan">
                <p>Double-sided, two page letter written in cursive, using dark ink.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <!-- Consult Dr. Caughie, Emily, or Rebecca to verify metadata specifics -->
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy source="https://arc-staging.dh.tamu.edu/index.php/Submitting_RDF">
                    <category source="collex" xml:id="discipline">
                        <catDesc>History/Book History</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category source="collex" xml:id="genre">
                        <catDesc>Correspondence</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category source="collex" xml:id="text">
                        <catDesc>https://gitlab.com/ctsdh/lili-elbe-code/raw/master/XSLT_sandbox/plainText/output/1933-10-22GWegenerKnudsen.txt</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category source="dc" xml:id="date">
                        <catDesc>1933</catDesc>
                    </category>
                   
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <!-- Verify with Rebecca that your document does not need additional editorial declarations. Most of the editions have additional children elements here (i.e. segmentation) -->
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>We have removed the hyphenation that appears in the printed text during
                        digitization and encoding. Original hyphenation can be consulted in the facsimile
                        images.</p>
                </hyphenation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="original">
                <div rend="head" style="letter"><pb facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/letters/1933-10-22GWegenerKnudsenL101.JPG"/>
                    <p>Marrakech <date>22/10 1933</date></p>
                    <p>P.S Læs nu <persName key="briffautG">Briffaut</persName>s Brev, og om du vil skriv selv til 
                        ham. Du ser, hvad han siger om Decameron! 
                        men måske var den noget for <placeName key="england">England</placeName>?? 
                        Hold mig altid a jour med 
                        Din Adresse.</p>
                </div>
                <div rend="body">
                    <p>Kære Paul,</p>
                    <p>Tak for Brev, som jeg har faaet igaar aftes. 
                    Jeg gaar nu ganske forretningsmæssigt til Værks og 
                    søger at besvare dine Spørgsmaal i Rækkefølge, 
                    for derefter at fortælle Dig andre Ting. Med Hensyn 
                    til mine Priser forstaar Du, det er lidt vanskeligt i 
                    Øjeblikket med den svingende Kurs. Men man maa 
                    jo tage Krisen i Betragtning og se at slaa Penge paa 
                    een eller anden Maade. Da jeg skrev til dig om <placeName key="piazzaLEdition">Piazza</persName>s 
                    Pris for “<persName key="andersen">Andersen</persName>”, saa har jeg vist taget Fejl. <placeName key="piazzaLEdition">Piazza</placeName> 
                    betalte mig c. 1500 francs per Tegning, hvilket var 
                    Maximum af, hvad man paa det Tidspunkt betalte. Deri 
                    var iberegnet, at han beholdt Originalerne. Dette gælder 
                    for “hans Texter”. Han betalte mig apart for alle Smaa-
                    Tegninger: Têtes de chapitre, culs de lampe etc. Jeg husker
                    ikke hvad han betalte mig for de Smaating. Det var 
                    en “Prix global”. – Paa det Tidspunkt representerede
                    1500 francs c. 200 Kr. Lidt derover. Nu har
                    jo imidlertid alt forandret sig, Kursen er en
                    ganske anden og der er – Krisen.</p>
                   <p>Altsaa: 1) Minimumspris burde være for en
                    Tegning nu c. 100 Kr. Størrelse c. 16 × 23 cm. (Mine
                    Øjne taaler ikke at lave dem mindre). Med Hensyn til Farvernes
                    Antal, saa spiller det igen Rolle i Prisen.</p>
                    <p>2) Du forstaar herudfra, at min Maximumspris 
                    burde være fra 200 til 250 Kr. pr. Tegning. Men
                    <pb n="2" facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/letters/1933-10-22GWegenerKnudsenL102.JPG"/>
                    den tror jeg ikke det kan nytte, at Du insisterer paa i
                    <placeName key="scandinavia">Skandinavien</placeName> i Øjeblikket. Maaske i <placeName key="england">England</placeName>. – I
                    Maximumsprisen (250 Kr.) er Originalen indbefattet.
                    Minimumsprisen (100 Kr.) gælder Reproductionsretten og
                    Originalen tilhører mig. –––</p>
                    <p>3) Dette drejer sig altsaa kun om Tegninger direkte udførte
                    for Forlaget. – Du ved jo sikkert, at man altid i <placeName key="england">England</placeName>
                    har betalt Tegninger langt højere end i <placeName key="france">Frankrig</placeName>. – Kun
                    har jeg aldrig haft Lyst til at leve i <placeName key="england">England</placeName>. Voilà!
                    Ellers havde jeg naturligvis tjent ganske andre Penge.
                    Især da Konkurrencen der er uendelig langt mindre
                    end i <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName>, som jo er og bliver det store artistiske
                    rendez-vous fra alle Leder og Kanter. (Det er sågar ikke Franskmændene, som gir Tonen an i kunstnerisk
                    Henseende! Nej, det er alle de dygtigste Udlændinge, som
                    kommer dertil, fordi Byen er behagelig og har en gammel 
                    Tradition!) ––– Med Hensyn til Priser for Clichérne
                    saa kan jeg intet andet sige Dig, end hvad jeg sagde
                    Dig i sidste Brev efter <persName key="briffautG">Briffaut</persName>s Svar angaaende
                    Reproductionerne af de Ting han allerede har lavet.
                    Jeg vedføjer her et Brev som jeg lige har faaet fra
                    <persName key="briffautG">Briffaut</persName>. Jeg tænker Du kan læse hans Skrift. –––
                    Det er jo givet, at hvis man skulde kunne ordne det
                    med Reproductionerne hos <persName key="briffautG">Briffaut</persName>, maa jeg have
                    min Extrabetaling, - men det overlader jeg til Dig
                    at ordne. Du er som sagt langt mere Forretningsmand
                    end jeg. Du vil sikkert faa mere ud af det end jeg
                    selv kunde faa. ––– (Jeg har heri og i (2) ogsaa
                    besvaret Dit Spørgsmaal (4) angaaende Reproductionsretten 
                    og Ejendomsretten. “Politiken” betalte mig i sin Tid
                    fra 100 til 150 Kr. Reproductionsretten til sine Forsider
                    i Søndagsmagasinet. Originalerne var mine. Voilà.</p>
                    <p>Men det var altsaa da 100 Kr. var c. 700 Francs. –</p>
                    <p>5) Med Hensyn til mine Tegninger <pb n="3" facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/letters/1933-10-22GWegenerKnudsenL103.JPG"/>
                    2) til <persName key="andersen">Andersen</persName>, saa havde jeg aldrig nogen Kontrakt
                    med <persName key="piazza">Piazza</persName>, som var en gammel Hædersmand, og
                    hvis Ord var som en Kontrakt. (Jeg har heller aldrig
                    haft med <persName key="briffautG">Briffaut</persName>, som er ganske lige saa honnet). Vi
                    var simpelthen gode Venner og stolede gensidigt paa
                    hinanden. – Desværre døde <persName key="piazza">Piazza</persName>, netop som
                    jeg havde mine Illustrationer næsten færdige. Han
                    og hans Efterfølger betalte mig intégralement mit Arbejde.
                    Men jeg har altsaa ikke et skriftligt Ord imellem os. 
                    Den unge Efterfølger havde først en Del vanskeligheder
                    med Overtagelsen af det store Firma. Saa kom Krisen.
                    Derfor ligger Bogen stadig og sover hos ham. Jeg vil
                    nu skrive til ham og se, om der skulle være
                    mulighed for at trække Tegningerne fra ham. Lad
                    os nu se!</p>
                   <p> Det er som sagt den smukkeste Bog jeg har lavet, –
                    og jeg raser over at se den i 4 Aar begravet i en
                    Bagbutik, uden at komme ud. De sidste Ting blev
                    leveret netop nu for 4 Aar siden. Jeg havde lagt meget
                    andet tilside for at lave den. ––– Den vilde jo
                    kunne faa sikkert en stor succes i <placeName key="scandinavia">Skandinavien</placeName>
                    og i <placeName key="england">England</placeName>! Den er jo tilmed ganske uskyldig.
                    Jeg vil gøre, hvad jeg kan for at faa Tegningerne.
                    Men jeg tør naturligvis intet love. Med mindre Du 
                    kan give mig et tilbud, saa jeg eventuelt kan
                    betale Forlæggeren i <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName> et minimum for at faa
                    Tegningerne igen. Du kender jo Franskmænd og penge!!
                    Jeg vilde frygtelig gerne have den ud!</p>
                   <p> 6) Du taler om en eventuel Provision til en
                    Mellemmand i <placeName key="england">England</placeName>. Det lader jeg dig ganske om,
                    det er umuligt for mig herfra at sidde og ordne alt
                    sligt i Detailler. Du er en af de meget faa, som jeg
                    stoler paa, naar det gælder mine interesser. Se bare
                    at slaa nogle Penge for mig.<pb n="4" facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/letters/1933-10-22GWegenerKnudsenL104.JPG"/></p>
                    <p>À propos <placeName key="england">England</placeName>: Saa har en gammel fin
                    Englænderinde her ladet sig presentere hos mig for at tale
                    med mig om <persName key="lili">Lili</persName>s Bog, som for nylig er udkommen
                    i <placeName key="england">England</placeName>, og som skal have en stormende Succes og
                    være Dagens store Samtaleæmne. Man ved i <placeName key="london">London</placeName>, at
                    det er mig, <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda Wegener</persName>, som er <persName key="sparreGre">Grete</persName> i Bogen. Og
                    min gamle engelske Veninde beklagede voldsomt, at jeg ikke
                    kunde komme til <placeName key="london">London</placeName> i Øjeblikket, da hun paastaar,
                    at jeg vilde blive “Dagens Heltinde”. Ser Du Mulighed for
                    at “udnytte dette” paa en eller anden Maade for en
                    Edition eller lignende ??? Men i saa Fald maatte det
                    ikke vare for længe. Der skal jo altid smedes mens Jernet
                    er varmt. Dette “à titre d’indication”. ––– <persName key="lili">Lili</persName>s Bog, (som
                    jeg jo omtrent havde skrevet, og som kun er bleven banaliseret
                    og omlavet af den skidne Jødetamp som hedder <persName key="hoyerNiels">Nils Høyer</persName>)
                    giver mig saa at sige intet. Han har faaet det lavet saa
                    snedigt, at jeg omtrent intet faar og han overholder ikke
                    engang sin Kontrakt. Han skovler alt til sig. Min
                    tidligere Svoger, Ingeneur <persName key="thomsenTC">T.C. Thomsen</persName>, som <persName key="lili">Lili</persName> havde
                    overdraget Forretningsførelsen af Bogen med, synes at være
                    i Ledtog med <persName key="hoyerNiels">Høyer</persName>. Hvad vil du have, at jeg skal
                    gøre paa denne Afstand, kære? Jeg kan jo ikke sidde
                    herfra og lave Høyer en Proces! Du, som er jurist,
                    sig mig om der er noget at stille op? –––</p>
                    <p>Hvis du ser <persName key="knudsenV">Vibeke</persName>, saa hils hende kærligt fra  mig.
                    Jeg skriver snart til hende. Foreløbigt skal jeg
                    flytte til 1ste November. Men derefter skriver jeg. – Min
                    Adresse er og bliver den samme. Nando er jo altid
                    i Konsulatet et Par Gange om Dagen.</p>
                    <p>Hjærteligste Hilsner fra os begge samt fra to 
                    Hundedrenge og en rød Kattepige.</p>
                    <p>Din hengivne</p>
                    <signed><persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName></signed>
                   
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="translation">
                <div rend="head" style="letter">
                    <p><date>Marrakech 22 October 1933</date></p><p>PS Read <persName key="briffautG">Briffaut</persName>’s letter and if you like, write to
                        him yourself. You see what he says about Decameron!
                        but perhaps it would be something for <placeName key="england">England</placeName>??
                        Always keep me a jour [up to date] with
                        your address.</p>
                </div>
                <div rend="body">
                    <p>Dear <persName key="knudsenP">Paul</persName>,</p>
                    
                    <p>Thank you for your letter, which I got yesterday evening.
                    I will now proceed in a businesslike manner and
                    try to answer your questions one by one,
                    and tell you other things afterwards. As 
                    to my prices, you understand it is a little difficult at
                    the moment with the fluctuating rate of exchange. But you have
                    to take the crisis into account and try to make money one
                    way or the other. When I wrote to you about <placeName key="piazzaLEdition">Piazza</placeName>’s
                    price for “<persName key="andersen">Andersen</persName>”, I think I must have been wrong. <placeName key="piazzaLEdition>Piazza</placeName>
                    paid me about 1500 francs per drawing, which was
                    the maximum of what was paid then. Therein
                    was included that he kept the originals. This applies
                    to “his texts”. He paid me [apart] privately for all minor
                    drawings: Têtes de chapitre, culs de lampe [headings of chapters and vignettes] etc. I do not remember
                    what he paid me for those minor items. It was
                    a “Prix global” [overall price]. – At that time 
                    1500 francs represented about 200 crowns. A little more. But now
                    everything has changed as you know, the rate is 
                    quite different and there is – the crisis.</p>
                    <p>So: 1) A minimum price should now be for a
                    drawing about 100 crowns. Size about 16 × 23 cm. (My
                    eyes cannot stand making them smaller). As to the number 
                    of colours, it does not matter to the price.</p>
                    <p>2) From this you understand that my maximum price
                    should be from 200 to 250 crowns per drawing. But
                    <pb n="2" facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/letters/1933-10-22GWegenerKnudsenL102.JPG"/>
                    I think that it will be hopeless to insist on that in
                    <placeName key="scandinavia">Scandinavia</placeName> at the moment. Perhaps in <placeName key="england">England</placeName>. – In 
                    the maximum price (250 crowns) the original is included. 
                    The minimum price (100 crowns) covers the right of reproduction and 
                    the original belongs to me. –––</p>
                    <p>3) This only applies to drawings done directly 
                    for the publisher. – You probably know that in <placeName key="england">England</placeName> a
                    far higher price has always been paid for drawings than in <placeName key="france">France</placeName>. – Only
                    I have never felt like living in <placeName key="england">England</placeName>. Voilà!
                    Otherwise I would of course have earned quite different money.
                    Especially as there is infinitely less competition there
                    than in <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName>, which is and always will be the great artistic
                    rendez-vous in every way. (It is not even the French who set the tone in artistic 
                    terms! No, it is all the cleverest foreigners who
                    come here because the city is comfortable and has an old
                    tradition!) ––– As to prices for the clichés [negatives], 
                    I can tell you no more than what I said to
                    you in my last letter after <persName key="briffautG">Briffaut</persName>’s answer regarding
                    the reproductions of the things he had already done.
                    I enclose a letter here that I have just had from
                    <persName key="briffautG">Briffaut</persName>. I think you can read his handwriting. –––
                    It is certain, of course, that if it should be possible to arrange it
                    with the reproductions at <persName key="briffautG">Briffaut</persName>’s, I must have
                    my extra payment, – but I leave it to you
                    to arrange that. As I said, you are far more a business man
                    than I. You will probably get more out of it than I
                    would be able to have myself. ––– (In this and in (2) I have also
                    answered your question (4) regarding the right of reproduction
                    and the right of ownership. In the past, “Politiken” paid me
                    from 100 to 150 crowns for the right of reproduction to its covers
                    in Søndagsmagasinet [The Sunday Magazine]. The originals were mine. – Voilà.</p>
                    <p>But that was when 100 crowns were about 700 Francs. –</p>
                    <p>5) As to my drawings
                    <pb n="3" facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/letters/1933-10-22GWegenerKnudsenL103.JPG"/>
                    2) for <persName key="andersen">Andersen</persName>, I never had any contract
                    with <persName key="piazza>Piazza</persName> who was an old gentleman and
                    whose word was like a contract. (I have also never 
                    had with <persName key="briffautG">Briffaut</persName> who is just as honourable). We
                    were simply good friends and trusted 
                    each other respectively. – Unfortunately <persName key="piazza">Piazza</persName> died just as
                    my drawings were almost finished. He
                    and his successor paid me intégralement [in full] for my work. 
                    But I really do not have a written word between us. 
                    At first the young successor had some difficulties
                    with the take-over of the large company. Then the crisis came.
                    That is why my book still lies sleeping with him. I am going to
                    write to him now and see if there should be a 
                    possibility of pulling the drawings from him. Let
                    us see!</p>
                    <p>As I said, it is the most beautiful book I have made, – 
                    and I rage at seeing it buried for 4 years in the
                    back of a shop without being published. The last things were
                    delivered just now 4 years ago. I had put many 
                    other things aside to make it. ––– Probably that would 
                    have a great success in <placeName key="scandinavia">Scandinavia</placeName>
                    and in <placeName key="england">England</placeName>! It is even perfectly innocent after all.
                    I will do what I can to get the drawings.
                    But of course, I dare not promise anything. Unless you
                    can give me an offer, so that I can perhaps 
                    pay the publisher in <placeName key="paris">Paris</placeName> a minimum in order to get
                    the drawings back. You know Frenchmen and money!
                    I would terribly like to have it published!</p>
                    <p>6) You talk about a possible provision for an
                    intermediary in <placeName key="england">England</placeName>. I’ll leave that to you entirely,
                    it is impossible for me to arrange all 
                    such matters in detail from here. You are one of the very few whom I
                    trust when it comes to my interests. Just
                    make some money for me.<pb n="4" facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/letters/1933-10-22GWegenerKnudsenL104.JPG"/></p>
                    <p>Speaking of <placeName key="england">England</placeName>: A old
                    English lady has let herself be introduced to me to talk
                    to me about <persName key="lili">Lili</persName>’s book that has recently been published
                    in <placeName key="england">England</placeName>, and is supposed to be a tremendous success and
                    and today’s great topic of conversation. It is known in <placeName key="london">London</placeName> that it is me, <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda Wegener</persName>, who is <persName key="sparreGre">Grete</persName> in the book. And
                    my old English friend deeply regretted that I was
                    not able to come to <placeName key="london">London</placeName> at the moment as she claims
                    that I would be “the heroine of the day”. Are you able 
                    to “use this” in some way for an
                    edition or the like??? But in that case, do 
                    not take too long, it is always best to strike while the iron 
                    is hot. This is just for your information.. ––– <persName key="lili">Lili</persName>’s book, (which
                    I as you know had more or less written, and which has only been trivialised
                    and changed by the filthy Jew called <persName key="hoyerNiels">Nils Høyer</persName>)
                    gives me practically nothing. He has arranged things so
                    cleverly that I get almost nothing and he does not even
                    keep to his contract. He rakes everything in. My
                    former brother-in-law, engineer <persName key="thomsenTC">T.C. Thomsen</persName>, whom <persName key="lili">Lili</persName> had
                    entrusted with the business management of the book, seems to be
                    in collusion with <persName key="hoyerNiels">Høyer</persName>. What do you want me to
                    do at this distance, dear? After all I cannot sit
                    and make a lawsuit against <persName key="hoyerNiels">Høyer</persName> from here! You who are a lawyer
                    tell me if there is anything to be done? –––</p>
                    <p>If you see <persName key="knudsenV">Vibeke</persName>, then send her my love.
                    I will write to her soon. For now I am going to
                    move at the 1st of November. But after that I shall write. – My
                    address will remain the same. <persName key="portaF">Nando</persName> is always 
                    in the consulate a couple of times a day as you know.</p>
                   <p> The kindest regards from us both plus from two
                    dog boys and a red cat girl.</p>
                    <p>Yours sincerely</p>
                   <signed><persName key="wegenerG">Gerda</persName></signed>
                    
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
