<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../../schema/out/LEDA_ODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rendition="lilielbe.org/narrative/editions/A1.html"
    xml:base="https://gitlab.com/ctsdh/lili-elbe-code/raw/master/XSLT_sandbox/EditionNumbering/input/A1.xml">
    <!-- insert correct URLs, above, for your text -->
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title> Ekstra Bladet lørdag <hi rend="italics">Ekstra Bladet Saturday .</hi> (<date>28 Febuary 1931</date>)</title>
                <title type="alternative">Lili Elvenes, alias Einar Wegener, has passed away.
                    <hi rend="italics">A Tragic End to a Fantastic Life.</hi> (<date>September 1931</date>)</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="bastJørgen" role="AUT"
                        >Jørgen Bast</persName>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Translation completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="mo" role="TRL"
                        >Marianne Ølholm</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Translation reviewed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="mo"
                        >Marianne Ølholm</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription completed by </resp>
                    <persName ref="mo">Marianne Ølholm</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="co">Colin OConnell</persName>
                    <persName ref="swv">Susan VanDerveer</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding assistance and/or XML proofing completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="ccm">Caroline McCraw</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>XML transformed into HTML
                        <date><!-- exact transformation date generated during transformation; leave this one alone --></date>
                        by</resp>
                    <persName ref="rjp">Rebecca J. Parker</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>HTML proofing completed by</resp>
                    <persName ref=""><!-- Insert Proofers name and initials in @ref--></persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Images prepared by</resp>
                    <persName ref="mg">Matthew Gallagher</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Loyola University Chicago Libraries</sponsor>
                <sponsor>Loyola's Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Lili Elbe Digital Archive</authority>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
                <date when="2019-07-06">July 6th, 2019</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName select="source">Ernst Harthern Archives,
                        Arbetarrörelsens Arkiv och Bibliotek (Swedish Labour Movement's Archives and
                        Library)</orgName> in <placeName>Huddinge, Sweden</placeName>.</p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                        4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc source="Periodical" xml:lang="dan">
                <p>A clipping affixed to a thin piece of paper in the EHSA shows four columns, no photographs, with two holes punched at the bottom of the middle columns; the publication information is handwritten in black ink across the top, and some stains (possibly water damage) obscure some parts of the article</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy source="https://arc-staging.dh.tamu.edu/index.php/Submitting_RDF">
                    <category source="collex" xml:id="discipline">
                        <catDesc>History/Gender Studies</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category source="collex" xml:id="genre">
                        <catDesc>Essay/Nonfiction</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category source="collex" xml:id="text">
                        <catDesc>https://gitlab.com/ctsdh/lili-elbe-code/raw/master/XSLT_sandbox/plainText/output/filename.txt</catDesc><!-- insert correct URL -->
                    </category>
                    <category source="dc" xml:id="date">
                        <catDesc>
                            <![CDATA[<dc:date>date metadata</dc:date>]]><!-- Do not forget to change the text between the dc:date tags AND include the <![CDATA[ before the dc:date tage and ]]> after it. -->
                        </catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category source="dcterms" xml:id="isPartOf" xml:lang="dan">
                        <catDesc>Lili Elvenæs, alias Ejnar Wegener, er afgaaet ved Døden. <hi rend="italics">En tragisk Afslutning paa en fantastisk Livsskæbne.</hi></catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category source="dcterms" xml:id="isPartOf_trans" xml:lang="eng">
                        <catDesc>Lili Elvenes, alias Einar Wegener, has passed away. <hi rend="italics">A Tragic End to a Fantastic Life.</hi></catDesc>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <!-- Verify with Rebecca that your document does not need additional editorial declarations. Most of the editions have additional children elements here (i.e. segmentation) -->
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>We have removed the hyphenation that appears in the printed text during
                        digitization and encoding. Original hyphenation can be consulted in the facsimile
                        images.</p>
                </hyphenation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="original">
                <div rend="head" style="periodical">
                    <p>
                        <title>Berlingske Titende</title>
                        <date when="1932-09-14"></date>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div rend="headlines">
                    <list>
                        <item rend="primary">
                            <persName>Lili Elvenæs</persName>, alias <persName>Ejnar Wegener</persName>, er afgaaet ved Døden.
                        </item>
                        <item> 
                            <hi rend="italics">En tragisk Afslutning paa en fantastisk Livsskæbne.</hi>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div rend="body">
<text>
    <body>
        <div type="original">
            <div rend="body">
                <p><persName key="warnekros">Professor von Warnekros</persName> fortæller</p>
                <p><persName key="lili">Lili Elbe</persName>til ved et i Lægevidenskabens Annaler enestaaende Indgreb.</p>
                
                <p>DEN tilsyneladende ganske utrolige Historie om Maleren <persName key="wegenerE">Einar Wegeners</persName> fysiologiske Forvandling til kvinde efter en Operation optager i Dag alle Sind. Almindelige Mennesker, som ikke har lægevidenskabelige Forudsætninger, staar fuldkommen uforstaaende over for Fænomenet og spørger med Undren: Er det virkelig muligt, at noget saadant kan finde Sted?</p>
                <p>For at faa Spørgsmaalet belyst fra virkelig Avtoritativ Side, har vi valgt at henvende os til den Mand, som til syvende og sidst er den eneste, der i denne sag kan udtale sig med nogen Vægt – nemlig den Læge, der har foretaget Operationen, den berømte tyske Gynækolog, <persName key="warnekros">Professor Kurt v. Warnekros</persName>.</p>
                
                <p><persName key="warnekros">Professor v. Warnekros</persName> fortæller.</p>
                
                
                <p><persName key="warnekros">Professor v. Warnekros</persName> er Leder af “Staatliche Frauenklinik” i <placeName key="dresden">Dresden</placeName>, og da vi ringer op til Kliniken, faar vi straks Professoren i Tale. Vi beder ham fortælle, hvad han mener sig i Stand til, om det mærkelige tilfælde.</p>
                <p> Det skal jeg gerne gøre, svarer Professoren med største Beredvillighed – saa meget mere, som Tilfældet er ganske enestaaende og vistnok uden Sidestykke i Lægevidenskabens Annaler. Mit Bekendtskab med den Kvinde, der nu er <persName key="lili">Lili Elbe</persName>, men som tidligere var Maleren <persName key="wegenerE">Einar Wegener</persName>, stammer fra Paris, hvor jeg i sin Tid lærte hende at kende. Man havde fortalt mig om hendes sjælelige Lidelser, og hun var paa dette Tidspunkt saa langt ude i Depressionen, at hun truede med at berøve sig Livet, fordi hun ikke kunde finde sig tilrette i Tilværelsen.</p>
                
                <p>Fremragende franske Læger, som hun havde henvendt sig til, havde ikke kunnet yde hende nogen Hjælp – de stod paa det Standpunkt, at der ikke var noget at gøre – hun maatte finde sig i sin Skæbne … Hendes Familie og venner bad mig indtrængende om i hvert Fald at foretage en Undersøgelse, og da jeg havde den største Medlidenhed med det ulykkelige Menneske, bøjede jeg mig for deres Ønske.</p>
                <p>Jeg fandt da til min overraskelse, at skønt hun i det Ydre havde udpræget mandlige Træk, var disse Træk kun af sekundær natur – i Virkeligheden var hendes Anatomi en Kvindes. Der kunde</p>
                illustration]
                <p><persName key="wegenerE">Maleren Einar Wegener</persName></p>.
                
                <p>ikke for Fagmanden være mindste Tvivl om, at Naturen her havde ville skabe en Kvinde, men at der ved et eller andet ulykkeligt Tilfælde var kommet Kludder i Værket. Da jeg var kommet saa vidt, forstod jeg, at det ved et operativt Indgreb maatte være muligt at befri denne stakkels Kvinde for hendes aarelange Lidelser og give hende tilbage til livet som et nyt Menneske. Jeg forstod ogssa, hvilken Risiko der var forbundet med et saadant Eksperiment – thi et Eksperiment var det i Virkeligheden for mig, da jeg stod ganske uden Fortilfælde af denne Art – men jeg mente, at Chancen var større end Risikoen, og jeg tog Ansvaret paa mig.</p>
                <p>Nu bagefter er jeg stolt og glad over at kunne sige, at Eksperimentet lykkedes over al Forventning.…</p>
                
                <p>Da Kvindeligheden vaagnede –</p>
                <p>– De foretog Operationen paa Deres Klinik i <placeName key="dresden">Dresden?</placeName></p>
                <p>– Ja, hun indvilgede i at komme til mig og underkaste sig min Behandling. Det var en meget omfattende og vanskelig Operation, og den var ikke helt ufarlig for Patienten. Om dens Enkeltheder kan jeg naturligvis ikke udtale mig … jeg maa nøjes med at sige, at det lykkedes mig at fjerne de Træk af mandlig Natur, der fandtes hos den ulykkelige Kvinde, og i Stedet indpode hende visse elementære kvindelige Organer, som hun manglede.</p>
                <p>Og da Operationen var lykkeligt over-</p>
            </div>    
        </div>
    </body>
</text>
<text>
    <body>
        <div type="original">
            <div rend="body">
                <list>
                    <hi rend="italics">(Fortsættes Side 9)</hi>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <hi rend="bold"><persName key="lili">LILI ELBE</persName></hi>
                </list>
                <figure>
                    <figDesc><hi rend="bold">Vi bringer her i Tilslutning til Artiklen, nogle fotografier af 
                        <persName key="lili">Lili Elbe</persName>, taget efter den lykkeligt overstaaede Operation. De to 
                        første Billeder viser <persName key="lili">Lili Elbe</persName> i <placeName key="womensClinic">Klinikens</placeName> Have i <placeName key="dresden">Dresden</placeName>. Det 
                        tredje er taget under et Rekreationsophold i <placeName key="erzgebirge">Erzgebirge</placeName>, og det 
                        fjerde stammer fra et besøg i Barndomsbyen <placeName key="vejle">Vejle</placeName> for ganske 
                        kort tid siden.</hi>
                    </figDesc>
                </figure>
                <list>
                    <hi rend="bold">MANDEN, DER BLEV KVINDE</hi>
                    <hi rend="italics">(Fortsat fra Side 1).</hi>
                </list>
                <figure>
                    <figDesc><hi rend="bold"><persName key="warnekros">Prof. Kurt v Warnekros</persName>.</hi>
                        Malt af <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda Wegener</persName>.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <p>staaet, skete det mærkelige og vidunderlige, at hendes slumrende 
                    Kvindelighed pludselig vaagnede og begyndte at udfolde sig, 
                    saavel sjæleligt som legemligt. Hun var nu en fuldt normal Kvinde, 
                    og mens Livet tidligere var hende en Lidelse, har hun allerede 
                    fundet sin Sindsro og Sjælsligevægt igen. Alting tyder paa, at hun 
                    har mange gode og lyse Aar foran sig … og naar Forholdene ligger 
                    saaledes, maa man da ikke sige, at dette egenmægtige Indgreb i 
                    Naturens Orden – eller om de vil, <hi rend="itlaics">Uorden</hi> – har været fuldt 
                    forsvarligt?</p>
                <p>– Er Operationen gennemført i en saadan Udstrækning, at den 
                    paagældende Kvinde f. Eks. ogsaa vil kunne gifte sig med 
                    en mand, hvis hun føler Trang dertil?</p>
                <p>– Ja, teoretisk set er der intet i vejen herfor. Og i hvert Fald vil 
                    man ved en fornyet Operation nemt kunne fjerne de Hindringer, 
                    som eventuelt endnu maatte stille sig i Vejen. Men barnløst vil et 
                    saadant Ægteskab under alle Omstændigheder blive … <hi rend="italics">det</hi> er den 
                    eneste Vanskelighed, som Lægevidenskaben ikke formaar at 
                    overvinde – – ellers er intet umuligt!</p>
                <!-- key ID for Dr. Rank is not listed within the prosopography -CO 11/6/19 -->
                <p><hi rend="italics">Dr. Rank.</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <hi rend="bold">Hvad Juraen siger.
                        Hvordan man stiller sig i Tilfælde af Kønsskifte.</hi>
                </list>
                <p>Vi har henvendt os til en fremragende Jurist her i Byen og 
                    spurgt ham, hvorledes Juraen og de verdslige Øvrigheder stiller sig 
                    i Tilfælde som det, der er overgaaet fhv. Maler <persName key="wegenerE">Einer Wegener</persName>, 
                    nuværende <persName key="lili">Fru Lili Elbe</persName>?</p>
                <p>– Der findes ikke nogen Bestemmelse i dansk Ret om dette 
                    Forhold. Ægteskabsloven har en Regel om Ægteskabers 
                    Omstødelse, hvis Ægtefællerne f. Eks. har været for nær 
                    beslægtede – men denne Regel gælder jo ikke i et Tilfælde som 
                    <persName key="lili">Lili Elbes</persName>. Saa har Loven desuden en Regel om, at et Ægteskab 
                    kan omstødes, naar Folk er uegnede til samliv (Impotens), men i 
                    saa Tilfælde skal der meget hurtigt indgives Skilsmissebegæring. – 
                    Det vil være urigtigt at bringe Lovens Skilsmisseregler i 
                    Anvendelse – og den eneste rigtige Løsning vil være simpelthen at 
                    betragte Ægteskabet som ikke eksisterende, idet det jo er Lovens 
                    forudsætning, at Ægteskaber indgaas mellem Personer af 
                    forskelligt Køn. Hvis der foreligger en Domsafgørelse i dette 
                    Tilfælde, kan det kun skyldes, at man har ønsket en retslig 
                    Konstatering af, at Forudsætningen for, at der overhovedet Kunde 
                    være Tale om et Ægteskab, mangler.</p>
                <!-- Johanne Katrine Nielsdatter, Hørby parish, and local orphanage are not listed within the prosopography -CO 11/6/19 -->
                <p>Det er her i landet sket i adskillige
                    Tilfælde, at Personer har skiftet Køn. Der var saa langt tilbage som 
                    i 1820 et Tilfælde, hvor Kongen tillod, at <persName>Johanne Katrine 
                        Nielsdatter</persName> af <placeName>Hørby Sogn</placeName> efter Indberetning fra Sundhedskollegiet 
                    betragtedes som Mand, tog navnet Johannes og fritoges for 
                    Krigstjenesten. – Senere har der være f. Eks. en Sag fra et 
                    herværende <placeName>Børnehjem</placeName>, hvor det viste sig, at Forstanderinden i 
                    Virkeligheden var en mand – han levede siden som et pænt og 
                    skikkeligt Menneske her i Staden.</p>
                <p>Ofte har det vist sig meget vanskeligt at bestemme, om et Barn 
                    er dreng eller Pige. I saa fald vil Fremgangsmaaden være den, at 
                    man henvender sig til Retslægeraadet, og hvis dette kan afgive et 
                    bestemt Svar, er Sagen jo afgjort. Hvis der er Tvivl om Kønnet, 
                    Venter man til Vedkommende er en Snes Aar gammel – saa kan 
                    det som regel siges med Sikkerhed.</p>
                <p>Hvis det til den Tid konstateres, at en maaske gift person 
                    tilhører et andet køn end det, hvori vedkommende er blevet 
                    opdraget, indgives der Andragende til Ministeriet vedlagt de 
                    forskellige Bevisligheder – og den paagældende faar derefter kgl. 
                    Bevilling paa, at han eller hun anses for tilhørende det andet Køn. 
                    Samtidig faar vedkommende et nyt Navn, svarende til sit rette Køn.</p>
                <!-- Professor Viggo Bentson not listed within the prosopography -CO 11/6/19 -->
                <p>I Tilfælde, hvor Kønnet ikke med Sikkerhed kan konstateres, er 
                    man i vore Dage inde paa den Tankegang, at vedkommende slipper 
                    for mulige sociale Ulemper, f. Eks. fritages for krigstjeneste. Dette 
                    udrykker <persName>Professor Viggo Bentzon</persName> i sin Familieret saaledes, at 
                    vedkommende “kan ikke blive Soldat, men nok Jordemoder”.</p>
                <p>Der er intet i Vejen for, at den, der saaledes har skiftet Køn, kan 
                    indgaa nyt Ægteskab – det tidligere er jo erklæret for Nul og nix.</p>
                
                
                Ekstra Bladet Saturday 28 February 1931
                
                <hi rend="bold">THE MAN WHO BECAME A WOMAN</hi>
                
                <hi rend="bold">An interview with <persName key="warnekros">Professor von Warnekros</persName></hi>
                
                <hi rend="bold"><persName key="lili">Lili Elbe</persName>came into being by means of a procedure unique in the annals of medical science</hi>
                
                <p>THE seemingly quite incredible story of the painter <persName key="wegenerE">Einar Wegener’s</persName> physiological transformation into a woman after an operation occupies all minds today. Ordinary people who do not have medical qualifications are completely unable to understand the phenomenon and ask in wonderment: Is it really possible that something like that can take place?</p>
                <p>To have the question elucidated from a really authoritative side we have chosen to approach the man who is ultimately the only one who can speak with any authority in this matter – namely the doctor who performed the operation, the famous German gynaecologist <persName key="warnekros">Professor Kurt v. Warnekros</persName>.</p>
                
                <p>An interview with <persName key="warnekros">Professor von Warnekros</persName></p>
                
                <p><persName key="warnekros">Professor v. Warnekros</persName> is head of “Staatliche Frauenklinik” in <placeName key="dresden">Dresden</placeName>, and when we call the clinic, we immediately get to speak to the professor. We ask him to tell us what he thinks himself capable of, about this strange case.</p>
                <p>– I’ll be happy to do so, the professor answers very promptly – all the more as the case is quite unique and I believe unequalled in the annals of medical science. My acquaintance with the woman who is now <persName key="lili">Lili Elbe</persName> but who was formerly the painter <persName key="wegenerE">Einar Wegener</persName> stems from <placName key="paris">Paris</placName> where I got to know her some time ago. I had been told about her mental sufferings, and she was at this time so far into depression that she threatened to take her own life because she was unable to find her place in life.</p>
                
                <p>Excellent French doctors that she had approached had not been able to help her – they took the view that nothing could be done – she had to resign herself to her fate … Her family and friends entreated me to at least perform an examination, and as I had the greatest compassion for the unhappy person, I deferred to their wish.</p>
                <p>To my surprise I then found that although externally she had definite male traits, these traits were only of secondary nature – in reality her anatomy was that of a woman. There could</p>
                <figure>
                    <list>
                        <hi rend="bold">The painter <persName key="wegenerE">Einer Wegener</persName></hi>
                    </list>
                </figure>
                <p>not be the least doubt to the expert that nature here had wanted to create a woman but that by some unfortunate accident the work had been messed up. When I had come so far, I understood that by a surgical operation it must be possible to free this poor woman from her sufferings that had lasted for years and give her back to life as a new person. I also understood the risk connected to such an experiment – because an experiment it actually was for me as I had no precedents at all of this kind – but I thought that the chance was greater than the risk and I assumed the responsibility.</p>
                <p>Now afterwards I am proud and happy to be able to say that the experiment was a success beyond all expectations….</p>
                
                
                <hi rend="bold">When Femininity awoke –</hi>
                <p>– You performed the operation at your clinic in <placeName key="dresden">Dresden?</placeName></p>
                <p>– Yes, she agreed to come to me and subject herself to my treatment. It was a very extensive and difficult operation, and it was not quite without risk to the patient. I cannot comment on its details of course … I have to restrict myself to saying that I succeeded in removing the traits of male nature that existed in this unfortunate woman, and instead implant in her certain elementary female organs which she lacked.</p>
                <p>And when the operation was successfully over,</p>
            </div>
        </div>
        <div type="translation">
            <div rend="body">
                <list>
                    <hi rend="italics">(To be continued on page 9)</hi>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <hi rend="bold"><persName key="lili">LILI ELBE</persName></hi>
                </list>
                <figure>
                    <figDesc><hi>In connection with the article we here provide some 
                        photographs of <persName key="lili">Lili Elbe</persName> taken after the successfully completed 
                        operation. The first two pictures show <persName key="lili">Lili Elbe</persName> in the garden 
                        of the <placeName key="womensClinic">clinic</placeName> in <placeName key="dresden">Dresden</placeName>. The third one is taken during a rest 
                        cure in <placeName key="erzgebirge">Erzgebirge</placeName>, and the fourth one comes from a visit in the 
                        native town <placeName key="vejle">Vejle</placeName> quite a short time ago.</hi>
                    </figDesc>
                </figure>
                <list>
                    <hi rend="bold">THE MAN WHO BECAME A WOMAN</hi>
                    <hi rend="italics">(Continued from page 1)</hi>
                </list>
                <figure>
                    <figDesc><hi rend="bold"><persName key="warnekros">Professor Kurt v Warnekros</persName>.</hi>
                        Painted by <persName key="wegenerG">Gerda Wegener</persName>.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <p>the strange and wonderful thing happened that her dormant 
                    femininity suddenly awoke and began to unfold, mentally as well 
                    as physically. She was now a completely normal woman, and while 
                    before life was painful to her, she has already found her peace of 
                    mind and mental equilibrium again. Everything indicates that she
                    has many good and bright years ahead of her … And as things 
                    stand, can you deny that this arbitrary intervention in the natural 
                    order of things – or if you like, <hi rend="italics">disorder</hi> – has been completely 
                    justifiable?</p>
                <p>– Has the operation been carried out to such an extend that the 
                    woman in question will for instance also be able to marry a man if 
                    she desires to?</p>
                <p>– Yes, theoretically nothing stands in the way of this. And at 
                    least it will be possible by a new operation to remove the obstacles 
                    that may still stand in the way. But such a marriage will necessarily 
                    be childless … <hi rend="italics">that</hi> is the only difficulty that medical science is not 
                    able to overcome – – otherwise nothing is impossible!</p>
                <!-- key ID for Doctor Rank is not lisited within the prosopography -CO 11/6/19 -->
                <p><hi rend="italics">Doctor Rank.</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <hi rend="bold">What the Law Says.
                        <anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="3"/>What the Line Is in Case of Sex Change.</hi><anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="3"/><note type="editor" source="plc" corresp="comment_3"><anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="4"/>"Where to draw the line in the case of sex change"?</note><anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="4"/><note type="translator" source="mo" corresp="comment_4">I thought this was difficult to translate. The meaning is closer to "what is the general approach or policy/what are the rules or the procedure".</note>
                </list>
                <p>We have approached a distinguished lawyer in this city and 
                    asked him how the law and the temporal authorities stand in cases 
                    like the one that has befallen the former painter <persName key="wegenerE">Einar Wegener</persName>, the 
                    present <persName key="lili">Mrs. Lili Elbe</persName>?</p>
                <p>– There is no provision in Danish law about this matter. The 
                    marriage act has a rule about the annulment of marriages if the 
                    partners for instance have been too closely related – but this rule 
                    does not apply in a case like <persName key="lili">Lili Elbe’s</persName> of course. Besides, the law
                    also has a rule that a marriage can be annulled when people are
                    unfit for married life (impotence), but in that case a petition for
                    divorce must be filed very quickly. – It would be incorrect to use 
                    the divorce rules of the law – and the only correct solution would 
                    be simply to regard the marriage as non-existent, as it is the
                    precondition of the law that marriages are entered into by persons
                    of different sex. If a verdict exists in this case, the explanation can 
                    only be that <anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="5"/>a legal establishment has been wanted of the fact that<anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="5"/><note type="editor" source="plc" corresp="comment_5"><anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="6"/>This wording sounds odd in English. Could we say, "a legal precedent is lacking [or wanting] for this to be considered a marriage at all"?</note><ancor type="commentRangeEnd" n="6"/><note type="translator" source ="mo" corresp="comment_6">It literally means that somebody wanted this to be clarified or established. The passive form is perhaps confusing. The Danish sentence has an impersonal subject "man".</note>
                    the preconditions for this to be considered a marriage at all are 
                    lacking.</p>
                <!-- Johanne Katrine Nielsdatter, Hørby parish, and local orphanage are not listed within the prosopography -CO 11/6/19 -->
                <p>In this country it has happened in several 
                    cases that persons have changed their sex. As far back as in 1820
                    there was a case where the king permitted that <persName>Johanne Katrine 
                        Nielsdatter</persName> of <placeName>Hørby parish</placeName>, after report from the health 
                    department, was considered a man, took the name of Johannes and 
                    was exempted from military service. – Later there has been for
                    example a case from a local <placeName>orphanage</placeName> where it appeared that the
                    matron in reality was a man – he later lived as a decent and honest
                    person in this city.</p>
                <p>Often it has proven very difficult to determine if a child is a 
                    boy or a girl. In that case the procedure will be that an inquiry 
                    is made to the medico-legal council and if this can give a
                    definite answer, the matter is settled of course. If there is doubt
                    about the gender, you wait until the person concerned is about 
                    twenty years old – then it can usually be determined with certainty. 
                </p>
                <p>If by then it is established that a married person perhaps 
                    belongs to another gender than the one in which the person 
                    concerned has been raised, a petition is presented to the ministry 
                    with the different pieces of evidence enclosed – and subsequently
                    the person in question gets a royal licence stating that he or she is 
                    considered to belong to the other <anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="7"/>gender<anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="7"/><note type="editor" source="plc" corresp="comment_7"><anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="8"/>Is the Danish "gender" or "sex"? We would say gender, but we can use sex if that's the word here because sex was generally used for gender at the this time.</note><anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="8"/><note type="translator" source="mo" corresp="comment_8">Danish does not have the same distinction. The word “køn” can be either sex or gender so we have to choose which is better in the context.</note>. At the same time, the
                    person concerned gets a new name corresponding to his or her true 
                    gender.</p>
                <!-- Professor Viggo Bentzon not listed within the prosopography -CO 11/6/19 -->
                <p>In cases where the gender cannot be established with certainty, 
                    today the thinking is entertained that the person concerned avoids
                    possible social disadvantages, for example is exempted from 
                    military service. <anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="9"/>This<anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="9"/><note type="editor" source="plc" corresp="comment_9"><anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="10"/>Is it "this"? "This professor" sounds odd here. Would "Viggo Bentzon, a professor of family law, says the person concerend "cannot be a soldier but [could probably be] a midwife"?</note><anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="10"/><note type="translator" source="mo" corresp="comment_10">"This" is the situation described in the previous sentence. I don't know if that can be included. Perhaps: Professor Viggo Bentzon expresses this in his family law by saying that the person concerned "cannot be a soldier but could probably be a midwife"</note><persName>professor Viggo Bentzon</persName> expresses in his 
                    family law in the way that the person concerned “cannot be a 
                    soldier but probably midwife”.</p>
                <p>There is no reason why the person who has changed his or her
                    gender in this way should not enter a new marriage – the previous
                    one has been declared nothing.</p>
            </div>    
        </div>
    </body>
</text>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>



