<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="LEDA_ODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rendition=""
    xml:base="">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>
                <date> when="1932-07-16"</date> Letter to <persName key="schumannH">Harry Shumann</persName>
            </title>
            <author>
                <persName key="hoyerNiels" role="AUT">Niels Hoyer</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt>
                <resp>Photographed by</resp>
                <persName ref="plc">Pamela L. Caughie</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                <resp>Images prepared by</resp>
                <persName ref="mg">Matthew Gallagher</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                <resp>Transcription completed by</resp>
                <persName ref="twj">Tatjana Willms-Jones</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                <resp>Translation completed by</resp>
                <persName ref="twj">Tatjana Willms-Jones</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                <resp>Translation reviewed by</resp>
                <persName ref="Kj">Kristin Jacobson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
                <persName ref="lpb">Laura Patricio-Bellizzi</persName>
                <persName ref="pmh">Phylicia Hall</persName>
                <persName ref="mek">Molly Kaull</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                <resp>Encoding assistance and/or XML proofing completed by</resp>
                <persName ref="pmh">Phylicia Hall</persName>
                <persName ref="mek"> Molly Kaull</persName>
                <persName ref="ccm">Caroline McCraw</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                <resp>XML transformed into HTML
                    <date>2019-10-29</date> by</resp>
                <persName ref="">         </persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                <resp>HTML proofing completed by</resp>
                <persName ref="lpb">Laura Patricio-Bellizzi</persName>
                <persName ref="co">Colin OConnell</persName>
            </respStmt>            
            <sponsor>Loyola University Chicago Libraries</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Loyola's Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities</sponsor>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Lili Elbe Digital Archive</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date>July 6th, 2019</date>
            <availability>
                <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName select="source">Ernst Harthern Archives, Arbetarrörelsens Arkiv och Bibliotek (Swedish Labour Movement's Archives and Library)</orgName> in <placeName>Huddinge, Sweden</placeName>.</p>
                <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons
                    Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc source="Manuscript" xml:lang="dan">
            <p><!-- PLC provided description goes here. --></p>
        </sourceDesc>         
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy source="https://arc-staging.dh.tamu.edu/index.php/Submitting_RDF">
                <category source="collex" xml:id="discipline">
                    <catDesc>History/Book History</catDesc>
                </category>
                <category source="collex" xml:id="genre">
                    <catDesc>Correspondence</catDesc>
                </category>               
                <category source="collex" xml:id="text">
                    <catDesc><!-- URL to Plain Text will go here.--></catDesc>
                </category>
                <category source="dc" xml:id="date">
                    <catDesc>
                        <![CDATA[<dc:date>nodate</dc:date>]]>
                    </catDesc>
                </category>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <hyphenation>
                <p>We have removed the hyphenation that appears in the printed text during
                    digitization and encoding. Original hyphenation can be consulted in the facsimile
                    images.</p>
            </hyphenation>
        </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>      
</teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="original">
                <div rend="head" style="letter">
                    <p><persName key="hoyerNiels">NIELS HOYER</persName> (ERNST HARTHERN)</p>                            
                    <p><placeName key="copenhagen">Kopenhagen</placeName> <date>16.7.32</date></p>
                    <p><persName key="reissnerCarl">Carl Reissner</persName> Verlag</p> 
                    <p><hi rend="underline"><placeName key="dresden">Dresden</placeName> N.</hi></p>
                </div>
                <div rend="body">
                    <p>Lieber Herr <persName key="schumannH">Schumann</persName>!</p> 
                    <p>Heute reise ich in meinen Urlaub. Meine Adresse lautet bis auf weiteres:</p>
                    
                    <p><persName key="hoyerNiels">Niels Hoyer (Ernst Harthern) </persName>
                        Badepensionat Grönnestrand 
                        <hi rend="underline">Per Fjerritslev (Nordjütland)</hi>
                        <placeName key="denmark">Dänemark</placeName>
                    </p>
                    
                    <p>Ich bitte, genau so zu adressieren! 
                        Die erste Korrektur habe ich ja, -bis auf Vorwort und die paar Ein-bzw.“Hinzu-fügungen“ gelesen; von der 2. Korrektur dagegen nur die ersten 6 Bogen. Dann setzen alle weiteren Sendungen aus. Weshalb? H i e r  kann ich nicht länger warten. Sie müssen mir also den Rest der 2. Korrektur an meine obige Adresse senden lassen.</p> 
                    
                    <p><persName key="brandstetterO">Brandstetter</persName> hatten mich in eine nette Aufregung gebracht: plötzlich schrieb man mir, die Sendung mit meinem Vorwort und der Titelei sei nicht einge-troffen, es wurde telegrafiert und telefoniert, -bis sich herausstellte, dass <persName key="brandstetterO">Brandstetter</persName> Ihnen ja meine “korrigierte Korrektur“ mit Zufügungen und Vor-wort gesandt habe; also liegt alles bei Ihnen.</p> 
                    
                    <p>So, wie Vorwort, Anfang und Ende jetzt ist, erscheint es mir gut und wirkungs-voll zu sein. Ein l a n g e s  Vorwort meinerseits 
                        hätte den Dokument-Charak-ter des Buches gestört. Die Propaganda-Texte sind inzwischen auch bei Ihnen eingetroffen.</p> 
                    
                    <p>Ich vermisse <anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="1"/>immer noch Ihre Antwort auf meine<anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="1"/><note type="translator" source="twj" corresp="comment_1">Highlighed with orange crayon</note> verschiedenen Fragen, <anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="2"/>so<anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="2"/><note type="translator" source="twj" corresp="comment_2">Word "Honorare" added in handwritten black ink next to this word</note>vor allem, <anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="3"/>welche<anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="3"/><note type="translator" source="twj" corresp="comment_3">"u. a" added before "welche"</note>Bildbeilagen kommen. Es ist doch selbstverständlich, dass ich als Autor erfahre, welche Bilder Sie meinem Buche beifügen.- Nur 2 Reproduktionen habe ich bisher gesehen.</p> 
                    
                    <p>Wann erscheint das Buch? Ich bitte auch um Einsendung des Entwurfes des Umschlages.-</p> 
                    
                    <p>In <placeName key="grønnestrand">Grönnestrand</placeName>, das unmittelbar an der Nordsee zwischen Dünen, etwas südwest-lich von <placeName key="skagen">Skagen</placeName> liegt, will ich mich ausruhen und ein neues Schauspiel von mir fertig machen; der Chronos Verlag (Deutsche Verlagsanstalt) hat gerade ein Schauspiel von einem dänischen Autor und mir herausgebracht, es an <placeName key="america">Ame-rika</placeName>, <placeName key="france">Frankreich</placeName> etc. verkauft.-</p> 
                    
                    <p>Wie steht es jetzt mit der Vorabdrucksmöglichkeit meines <persName key="lili">Lili Elbe</persName> Buches? Lässt sich das noch machen?</p> 
                    
                    <p>Übrigens heisst die Heldin des “gemeinsamen Stückes“ bei Chron<anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="4"/>o<anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="4"/><note type="translator" source="twj" corresp="comment_4">"o" typed over "i"</note>s ebenfalls <persName key="lili">Lili</persName>…Hoffentlich bringen beide <persName key="lili">Lili</persName> allen Beteiligten Glück….</p>
                    
                    <signed>Die besten Grüsse!
                        Ihr</signed>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="translation">
                <div rend="head" style="letter">
                    <p><persName key="hoyerNiels">NIELS HOYER</persName> (ERNST HATHERN)</p>                                
                    <p><placeName key="copenhagen">Copenhagen</placeName> <date>7/16/32</date></p>  
                    <p><persName key="reissnerCarl">Carl Reissner</persName> Publisher</p>
                    <p><hi rend="underline"><placeName key="dresden">Dresden</placeName> N.</hi></p> 
                </div>
                <div rend="body">
                    <p>Dear Mr.<persName key="schumannH">Schumann</persName>!</p>
                    <p>Today I’m going on vacation. My address will be:</p> 
                        
                    <p><persName key="hoyerNiels">Niels Hoyer (Ernst Harthern)</persName> 
                        Badepensionat Gönnestrand 
                        <hi rend="underline">Per Fjerritslev (Nordjütland)</hi>
                        <placeName key="denmark">Denmark</placeName>
                    </p>
                        
                    <p>I kindly ask you, to address it exactly like this! 
                        I read the correction, except for the foreword and a couple of “add-ins”; from the second correction I only read the first 6 pages. 
                        Everything else that you have sent will not get to me. Why? 
                        I cannot wait h e r e  for this. You have to send the rest of the second correction to the above address.</p> 
                        
                    <p><persName key="brandstetterO">Brandstetter</persName> sent me into a little frenzy: all of a sudden, I received notice that my mail with the foreword wasn’t received, we faxed and telephoned, until it was discovered, that <persName key="brandstetterO">Brandstetter</persName> had sent you my “corrected corrections” with add-ins and the foreword; so all the documents are with you.</p> 
                        
                    <p>The way that the foreword, beginning and end is now, appears to be good and effective to me. A  l o n g  foreword on my part would have disturbed the book’s character. The texts for the advertisements have already been sent to you.</p> 
                        
                    <p>I am still missing the answers to my questions, especially about the questions concerning which pictures will be included. It goes without saying, that as the author, I will find out, which pictures you will include in my book.- I have only seen 2 photocopies so far.</p> 
                        
                        
                    <p>When will the book be published? I am also asking for a design for the cover page.-</p> 
                        
                    <p>In <placeName key="grønnestrand">Grönnestrand</placeName>, which is right at the North Sea between the dunes, a little southwest from <placeName key="skagen">Skagen</placeName>, I am going to relax and finish a new play; the Chronos publisher (a German publisher) just published a play by a Danish author and me, and sold it to <placeName key="america">America</placeName>, <placeName key="france">France</placeName>, etc.-</p> 
                        
                        
                    <p>How is the advance print of my <persName key="lili">Lili Elbe</persName> book looking? Is that still possible?</p> 
                        
                    <p>The heroine of the “combined play” with Chronos was also called <persName key="lili">Lili</persName>… I hope that both <persName key="lili">Lilis</persName> bring everyone involved luck….</p>
                    <signed>Kindest regards! 
                        Your</signed>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
