<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="LEDA_ODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>
               <date>(1932-03-17)</date> Letter to <persName>Sirs</persName>
            </title>
            <author>
               <persName key="hoyerNiels" role="AUT">Niels Hoyer</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Translation completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="twj">Tatjana Willms-Jones</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Translation reviewed by</resp>
               <persName ref="sm">Sabine Meyer</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription completed by </resp>
               <persName ref="twj">Tatjana Willms-Jones</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="kd">Kritika Dabral</persName>
               <persName ref="ml">Mylinh Lam</persName>
               <persName ref="mf">Megan Fries</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoding assistance and/or XML proofing completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="ccm">Caroline McCraw</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML transformed into HTML
                     <date><!-- exact transformation date generated during transformation; leave this one alone --></date>
                  by</resp>
               <persName ref="rjp">Rebecca J. Parker</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>HTML proofing completed by</resp>
               <persName ref="drr">Danielle Richards</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Loyola University Chicago Libraries</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Loyola's Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Lili Elbe Digital Archive</authority>
            <pubPlace>Chicago, IL, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="2019-07-06">July 6th, 2019</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International license.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc source="Manuscript" xml:lang="ger">
            <p>A one half-page, two-sided typed letter on Niels Hoyer stationery with "Lili Elbe"
               written across the top in red crayon and two holes punched in the top margin.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy source="https://arc-staging.dh.tamu.edu/index.php/Submitting_RDF">
               <category source="collex" xml:id="discipline">
                  <catDesc>History/Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category source="collex" xml:id="genre">
                  <catDesc>Correspondence</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- DR: Should letterhead <p>Niels Hoyer</p><p>/Ernst Harthern/</p> (as opposed to the typed header) be included in this file? -->
         <div type="original">
            <pb facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/letters/1932-03-17HoyerSirs01.jpg" style="page" n="1"/>
            <div rend="head" style="letter">
               <p><placeName key="copenhagen">Kopenhagen</placeName> /Havnegade 47</p>
               <p>
                  <date when="1932-03-17">17.3.32</date>
               </p>
            <p>Franck’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung</p>
            <p>
               <placeName key="stuttgart">Stuttgart</placeName>
            </p>
            </div>
            <div rend="body">
            <p>Sehr geehrte Herren!</p>
            <p> Für Ihre sehr liebenswürdigen Zeilen vom 15.3. danke ich Ihnen verbindlichst. Die
               Möglichkeit, Ihnen später einmal ein anderes Buch von mir anzubieten, liegt in
               absehbarer Zeit vor. Bei dem <persName key="lili">Lili Elbe</persName> Buch handelt
               es sich um ein Werk, das nicht im eigentlichen Sinne als literarisch angesprochen
               werden kann. Denn es ist ein „menschliches Dokument“ und keine Dichtung, wie
               romanhaft sich das Leben <persName key="lili">Lili Elbe</persName>s auch gestaltet
               hat. Aber gerade dieser Umstand hat das Buch hat das Buch in meiner dänischen Ausgabe
               bereits zu einem beträchtlichen Erfolg geführt, der sich erst voll in meiner
               deutschen Ausgabe sowie in der englischen, französischen etc.Übertragung auswirken
               wird. Der Inhalt ist fern von jeder Sensationshascherei. Wer dies erwartet, wird
               bitter enttäuscht werden. Schade, dass ich keine Gelegenheit fand, auch Ihnen mein
               Manuskript zur Beurteilung vorzulegen. –</p>
            <p> Sie richten dann an mich eine Frage. An sich vermittle ich Übersetzungen nicht,
               übersetze wohl dann und wann, falls der betr.deutsche Verlag das Original fest
               angenommen hat. Deshalb muss ich an Sie die Gegenfrage richten: können Sie
               skandinavische Werke aus dem Original für Ihre Verlagszwecke lesen, beurteilen
               lassen? -In diesem Falle könnte ich Ihnen skandinavische Bücher, die wert sind,
               übersetzt zu werden, vorlegen. Ich denke besonders <persName id="rasmussenKnud">Knud
                  Rasmussen</persName>s Eskimo-Mythen und Legenden, die ganz herrlich sind, und an
               die Hinterlassenschaft <pb facs="http://lilielbe.org/media/letters/1932-03-17HoyerSirs02.jpg" style="page" n="2"/> von <choice><orig>I.P. Jacobsen</orig><reg><persName key="jacobsenJP"
                        >J.P.Jacobsen</persName></reg></choice>, darunter eine „Evolutionslehre“ –
               wohl ein Torso, aber dennoch von sehr, sehr grosser dichterischer Qualität. Können
               Sie aus dem Original skandinavische Literatur beurteilen lassen, so will ich Ihnen
               gern die noch nicht im Deutschen veröffentlichten Arbeiten von <choice><orig>I.P. Jacobsen</orig><reg><persName key="jacobsenJP"
                  >J.P.Jacobsen</persName></reg></choice> zusenden. Auch <persName
                  id="rasmussenKnud">Rasmussen</persName> Bücher, die mir vorliegen.–</p>
            <p>Schliesslich noch eine Bitte: könnten Sie mir ein paar der Haupteditionen und die
               Richtung Ihres Verlages zusenden, damit ich die Art Ihrer Editionen, den Charakter
               und die Richtung Ihres Verlages klar erkennen kann?</p>
            <p>Ich hoffe, dass es einmal zu einer Zusammenarbeit kommt und erwarte in diesem Sinne
               gern bald Ihre Rückäusserung.</p>
            <signed>Hochachtungsvoll</signed>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div type="translation">
         <div rend="head" style="letter">
         <p><placeName key="copenhagen">Copenhagen</placeName>/Havnegade 47</p>
            <p><date when="1932-03-17">3/17/32</date></p>
         <p>Franck’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung</p>
         <p><placeName key="stuttgart">Stuttgart</placeName></p>
         </div>
         <div rend="body">
         <p> Dear Sirs!</p>
         <p> I would like to thank you for your kind words from the 3/15. The possibility of me
            offering you another one of my books lies in the near future. The <persName key="lili"
               >Lili Elbe</persName> book is a work that cannot really be considered a literary
            work. It is a “human document” and not a novel, as story-like as <persName key="lili"
               >Lili Elbe</persName>’s life may have unfolded itself. But exactly because of this of
            situation, the Danish version has been such a huge success, which will only be amplified
            by the German, English and French versions. The content is far from sensationalism.
            Whoever expects this, will be bitterly disappointed. It’s unfortunate, that I wasn’t
            able to send you my manuscript for feedback.-</p>
         <p>You asked me a question. I usually don’t pass on translated works, I will however, if
            the German publishing company in question has already accepted the original work. That
            is why I have to ask you a counter question: can you read and analyze some original
            Scandinavian works for your publishing company? In this case, I could refer some
            Scandinavian works, that are worth translating, to you. I think especially <persName
               id="rasmussenKnud">Knud Rasmussen</persName>’s “Eskimo-Mythen und Legenden”, which
            are wonderful, and the legacy of <choice><orig>I.P. Jacobsen</orig><reg><persName key="jacobsenJP"
               >J.P.Jacobsen</persName></reg></choice>, which includes the “Evolutionslehre”- it may be unfinished,
            but it is still of very, very large literary quality. If you can assess the original
            Scandinavian works, then I would like to send you the works of <choice><orig>I.P. Jacobsen</orig><reg><persName key="jacobsenJP"
               >J.P.Jacobsen</persName></reg></choice>, that still have not been published in
            German. The same goes for the book I have of <persName id="rasmussenKnud"
               >Rasmussen</persName>.</p>
         <p>Lastly, another request: could you send me some of your publishing company’s main
            publications, so that I can clearly gage the tone and character of your company.</p>
         <p>I hope that we will be able to work together soon, and am looking forward to your
            reply.</p>
         <signed> Yours sincerly</signed>
      </div>
      </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
